<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to several material passages in a book published some time since by W.P. entituled, A brief examination and state of liberty spiritual, both with respect to persons in their private capacity, and in their church-society and communion, &amp;c. by J.H.</title>
            <author>Hogg, John, fl. 1675-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44111</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2368</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13730</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12539922</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12539922</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62948</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44111)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62948)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 670:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to several material passages in a book published some time since by W.P. entituled, A brief examination and state of liberty spiritual, both with respect to persons in their private capacity, and in their church-society and communion, &amp;c. by J.H.</title>
                  <author>Hogg, John, fl. 1675-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 51 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: prelim. p. [8].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Penn, William, 1644-1718. --  Brief examination and state of liberty spiritual.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62948:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62948:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO Several Material Paſſages IN A BOOK, Publiſhed ſome time ſince by <hi>W.P.</hi> ENTITULED, <hi>A Brief Examination and State of Liberty ſpiritual, both with reſpect to Perſons in their private Capacity, and in their Church-Society and Communion,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62948:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62948:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>FRIENDS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> being esteemed ſuch as profeſs the Spirit of Truth, the guide into all Truth, having met with this Book, Entituled, <hi>A brief Examination and ſtate of Liberty ſpiritual, both with reſpect to Perſons in their private Capacity, and in their Church Society and Communion;</hi> and finding the Author tells us, his aim was to aſſert Truth, detect Error, and point at ſome Shoals and Sands, that ſome have too boldly run upon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Noting the great difference among Friends, touching the latter, we could do no leſs than give it a ſerious Peruſal, in which we found, inſtead of aſſerting the Truth freely, detecting Error fairly, or pointing at any dangerous Sand or Shoal certainly; the tendency of our Author's Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe, was rather to remove thoſe true Marks we had, then otherwiſe; by endeavouring to bring in a Blind Obedience, and an Implicit Faith, to what he calls the Church, (which ſeems rather implied too, than fairly ſet forth that we can find.)</p>
            <p>On this account, conſidering how eaſie 'tis for many on a Religious ſcore, to take things for granted from Perſons valued on that account, rather than give themſelves the trouble of tryal, by a true ſearch, according to the due weight of the Matter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62948:3"/>
            <p>We ſay, conſidering the danger of this, we could do no leſs than take notice of ſeveral parts of the ſaid Book, deſiring they may be well weighed and conſidered, by ſuch as believe the Spirit of Truth, is that only guide into all Truth. How far we was obliged to do this at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, by an immediate Motion from God, we ſhall not now determine, nor Impoſe upon any; for as we find the name of the Lord in this caſe is almoſt become as a Reproach, being ſo often uſed of late to ſo little purpoſe, ſo we would not adminiſter further Occaſion in that reſpect, to thoſe that are without, to ſpeak evil of the way of Truth, becauſe of ſome difference among ſuch as profeſs it; nor would we perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily impoſe upon our Brethren, who profeſſing the ſame Principles of Truth, may pretend to the like Certainty; for avoiding thoſe things, we chuſe rather to commend wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t we have to ſay, to the witneſs of God in every mind, that being the likelieſt way to make room for Truth; and as ſoft words are ſaid to pacifie Wrath, ſo are they moſt like to be heard at this time.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, we have delivered our Judgment plainly, that the Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency and Import of our Author's Diſcourſe was, and is to bring in blind Obedience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which as it leads from the Truth, ſo it is wrong in it ſelf; and as every wrong is managed knowingly, or otherwiſe thro' ſome miſtake; if <hi>wrong is carried on</hi> knowingly, 'tis evil or wicked, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe deſigned; but from this cenſure, we may in Charity excuſe our Author, believing him both a better Man, and more a Chriſtian; but if not deſigned, it muſt be carried on and managed through ſome miſtake, and ſo we would have what is ſaid in the following Diſcourſe to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood.</p>
            <p>But then ſome may inquire, how our Author could be miſtaken, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Maſter of ſuch great Abilities? to which we anſwer, eaſily, through the mysterious working of the Enemy in the likeneſs of Truth; nor need this ſeem ſtrange to any, if they conſider how many have been deceived thereby, both great and ſmall, and ſome at times hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into things groſly evil, as killing their fellow Creatures; and yet at the ſame time, think they did God Service, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> How much more eaſie is it for Perſons to be deceived by the Enemy, in things that appear like good? The likeneſs of good and of Truth, is that which the evil one takes up, to keep his place, and ſave his Life, when he can keep no longer in the polluted State; for being a Spirit, he can turn into any likeneſs, and through the over-valuing of outward thing's
<pb facs="tcp:62948:3"/>on a Religious ſcore, has the Enemy ſlipped undiſcovered into all Forms of Religion, that have been in the World, and thereby kept alive his Kingdom, in the Wrath; Enmity, hard Speeches, Hatred, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs, that have been kept up among the various Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of it.</p>
            <p>Therefore, that great Mystery of Iniquity ſtands in the likeneſs of Truth; for if there was nothing like Truth, that is not Truth, there could be no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs among ſuch, as in any meaſure fear God; for as then there would be nothing but good and Evil, ſo ſuch as loved the Good, as they would deny the Evil, they would own the good to the leaſt degree of its appearance, knowing that as the Root of all Evil, was but one, ſo the Root of all good, was but one.</p>
            <p>But now beſides what is evil and good, as coming from each re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Root, there is a third thing, as we may ſay, that ſtands betwixt them. The outward appearance reſembles good to a great degree, but the Root is of the ſame Nature with the Evil, having only changed his appearance; and though good may ſometimes be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed here, as there is any thing of Sincerity in the Mind, yet the Root of Evil not being removed away, the covering of the Soul in the beſt ſenſe, is but as the linnen and woolen Garment, forbid to be worn under the Law: On this account, it is as needful to know the Enemy caſt out of our Hearts, as he appears like good, as it was to know him cast out, as he appeared as Evil; for as where the latter is not known, there wants the form of Truth; ſo where the former is not witneſſed, there wants the power of it. It is here that he deceives poor Man, ſitting as God in the <hi>Temple of God;</hi> and therefore, till he is caſt out, we cannot know our Names truly to be written in the <hi>Lamb's Book of Life.</hi> In this is the Victory, not only over <hi>Sin,</hi> but over <hi>Satan;</hi> for when he can keep no longer in the polluted State, nor deceive by the likeneſs of good, then can he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no more.</p>
            <p>This we muſt hope and look for, and the Turnings and overturnings in Profeſſion of Religion, ſince the ſtirring of God by his Spirit to Reformation, do ſhew that he is on his way to reign, whoſe Right it is a But to our Time this Likeneſs of Truth, this Enemy, as God ſitting in the Temple of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hath not been caſt out, nor could in any Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, becauſe all-a-long ſome outward Ceremoniel or ſhadowy things
<pb facs="tcp:62948:4"/>was joyned with the Spirit of Truth, as eſſential to Salvation, True Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the Government of Chriſt: But as the Enemy can go into any outward Form or Thing, therefore he could not be caſt forth whilſt thoſe outward Things were overvalued; but whether ſuch have acted againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstanding, or the Day was not ſo far dawned upon them, we ſhall not have determine, becauſe our Buſineſs is to conſider what the Lord has done for us; hath he not given us to believe that God's Holy Spirit is the only Guide into all Truth, the Subſtance of all Types and Figures, and the fulfiller of every addition for Righteouſneſs-ſake, truely reconciling to God? But if after we have ſeen or believed the Lord is that Spirit, the Heir of all things that is Good and Serviceable for mans Souls Good, that was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Law, Prophets, or in any External Order, Form, Rule or Shadowy thing; if after we have believed all this we ſet up Ceremonial Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantial or ſhadowy Things, as Terms of Communion and Eſſential to the Government of Chriſt, then we err on one Hand as they did on the other; they ſeemed to come ſhort, in not believing the thing to be done on this ſide the Grave, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And we err and come ſhort in concluding the Work is done before it is, which is a falſe Reſt, for as we have more Additions than we had in our Beginning, and as every adding of outward Rules ſhews a Want of Chriſt's Government by his Holy Spirit; therefore, in the beſt Senſe, if theſe Rules are added to perfect, and not only as an Expedient for the preſent Want, and ſo only to be uſed till Chriſt come in Power, to govern the Soul; inſtead of helping they will certainly hinder.</p>
            <p>For as there is no Rule that hath been, is, or ever ſhall be, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the Soul, by bringing it to God, but the Holy Spirit; ſo it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain there is no Government in this Caſe but that of Chriſt, but it ſhall have an End. From hence it is certain that no outward Rule, as it concerns a Holy Converſation on the Worſhip of God is of any Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, but until he come: therefore outward Rules, as above are ſet up, by us as a ſtanding Ordinance or but for a Time: If but for a Time, then their Service is but to ſteddy our Mind, that ſo in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of them we might daily wait for their fulfilling, by the coming of Christ, by his Holy Spirit: But if Rules, as above, are made as a standing Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, then are theſe outward things over-valued, and whilſt over-valued we cannot know Chriſt the <hi>Emanuel</hi> come to fulfil them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62948:4"/>
            <p>On this account it is that every latter Appearance of God is as Death to the former, and this is our Caſe, as well as any that did go before us, for the Subſtance of thoſe two great Diſpenſations of Law and Goſpel muſt be known in every Man that comes truly through the Work of Regeneration into the Kingdom of God, and therefore as the Natural Life is hard to be parted with, where a better is not hoped for, ſo where the Life of Religion stands in outward Things or Rules they are hard to be parted with while a better Life and Rule is not hoped for. Can any Man ſerve two Maſters, which in our caſe we deſire may be truly conſidered; and for that end we offer, as the Object of the Mind is, ſo is the Mind, whether it regard Converſation or the Worſhip of God, for if the Object of the Mind be an outward Rule the Mind can go no further than that Rule, for can any thing give forth more than it hath in it ſelf? therefore by outward Rules Man can go no further than a Legal Diſpenſation; and if Mantakes up his Reſt here, his Dependance is no higher than a Covenant of Works, and ſuch cannot know ſelf-ſlain, and as ſuch can never know boaſting excluded, they cannot know Salvation truly, by the free Grace of God: But if the Object of the Mind be God's Holy Spirit, and truly follows it, the Mind thereby will become wholly Spiritual, wherein the old Things paſs away and all becomes new, both as to outward things and alſo to heavenly things: Here the Tree is made Good, and its Fruit Good; Now the Root being Holy the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is Holy, for as is the Fountain ſo is the Stream, what was difficult before is now eaſie, and what ſeemed harſh before is now pleaſant, for the Root of evil being caſt out there remains nothing but Good: Here the Peace on Earth and good Will is known to all Mankind; we deſire therefore that outward Things may not be over-valued, for therein ſtand the uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that is amongst all that fear God, for as the over-valuing outward things hinders from coming into Communion and Fellowſhip with God, ſo it hinders the true Knowledge of the ſtirings of God in others, for when the Appearance or Converſation must be meaſured by certain Rules, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, what is Terms of Communion, or is accepted of God, may not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of Men; we know where the Heart is purified, the Mind made Holy by the indwelling of God's Holy Spirit, this is terms of Communion, or what is accepted of God, from hence proceeds a Holy Converſation with a Confeſſion to that Righteous Principle by which it is made ſuch, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as this is not accepted with Men, ſuch are not born of God, nor do they know that Holy City, whoſe Gates stands open by Day, for there is no Night there, this lets all in that are Good, but hinders what is not: But
<pb facs="tcp:62948:5"/>all Cities but this, as they have Day and Night, ſo they know not what they do, but ſhut their Gates as ſoon against the Good as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: That this great Evil may be avoided is all that is intended by what is here written, and that as we began in the Spirit ſo we may wait to be perfected thereby, that ſo as we have in any meaſure known him to have been our <hi>Alpha,</hi> we may know him to be our <hi>Omega</hi> alſo, for by no other way can the Deceiver be caſt out as he takes up the Profeſſion of the Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where the Term You is found in the following Diſcourſe, we intend the Author and thoſe of his Mind, whoever they are, whether many or few.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And as the Term We is alſo uſed, it may be underſtood in reſpect to thoſe of the ſame Mind with the Author of this Boook.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>There are ſeveral Faults committed by the Preſs, in Letters, Stops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which the Reader is deſired to amend in the Reading; and in page 5. line 8. for <hi>Author</hi> read <hi>Apostle.</hi> And pag. 49. lin. 8. for <hi>uncountable</hi> read <hi>unaccountable.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="pamphlet">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62948:5"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER to a BOOK, ENTITULED, <hi>A Brief EXAMINATION,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>AS to the Definition of Liberty ſpiritually explained, Page the firſt, we agree upon the matter.</p>
            <p>But Page 2. after the asking of ſeveral Queſtions, the Author comes to this reſult, That there is ſome things left to our freedom, and bounds it at this time to outward things of Life and Commerce, as what I ſhall eat, and when, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And then ſtates this Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But doth not freedom extend farther than this? For ſince God hath given me a manifeſtation of his Spirit to profit withall, and that I have the gift of God in my ſelf, ſhould I not be left to act according as I am free and perſwaded in my own mind in the things that relate to God, leaſt looking upon my ſelf as obliged by what is revealed unto another, though it be not revealed unto me, I ſhould be led out of my own mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and act upon another motion, and offer a blind ſacrifice to God?</hi> To which he anſwers thus.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is true in a ſenſe, that is, if thou art ſuch an one that canſt do nothing againſt the Truth, but for the Truth, then thou may'ſt ſafely be left to thy freedom in the things of God; and the reaſon is plain, becauſe thy freedom ſtands in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Law of Liberty, in the Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus, and in the Truth which is Chriſt Jeſus, which makes thee free indeed, that is, perfectly free from all that is bad, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62948:6"/>free to all that is holy, juſt, lovely, comly, and of good report: But if thou plead thy freedom againſt ſuch things, yea, obſtructeſt and ſlighteſt ſuch good, wholſom and requiſite things, thy freedom is naught, dark, perverſe, and out of Truth, and againſt the perfect Law of Love and Liberty.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> That this queſtion above is weighty, is clear, for the whole controverſie ſeems included in it; for where the gift of God is received to profit withall, they have liberty and freedom to chuſe or refuſe things according as they are perſwaded, or they have not; and all this is included in the queſtion; whereupon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to truth, if his deſign had been to aſſert it, the Queſtion ought to have been effectually anſwered, and all the parts of it free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fairly diſcuſſed, that Perſons might have known their true Liberty, with reſpect to <hi>Church-communion</hi> according to his Title Page: But on the contrary, in our Judgment, the Anſwer, if wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of that name, is ſlight and evaſive, no way deſerving to be reputed or accepted as a true Anſwer to this weighty Queſtion.</p>
            <p>For, Obſerve, the Queſtion is, Whether freedom and liberty do not extend further than outward things; that is, whether it do not reach to the things of God where the gift of God is received according to the Queſtion, which being ſet down above <hi>Verbatim,</hi> we allways refer to in this matter, both to avoid miſtake and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition.</p>
            <p>To this, obſerve we find no direct Anſwer, neither directly affirming or denying the Queſtion; what's there, 'tis true implies a grant, but not to the purpoſe; and it ſeems rather to take the Queſtion to be an Aſſertion than a Queſtion, in our Judgment; for it follows thus, that this Queſtion is true in a ſenſe, which to us is neither clear nor very proper, a Queſtion in ſome ſort being a matter undetermined till affirmed or denied: And thus at firſt we ſee the Queſtion is rather avoided than anſwered; for what cauſe we ſhall enquire afterward. And in the mean time, ſeeing his Anſwer takes the Queſtion to be an Aſſertion to humor it, we are content the Queſtion be affirmed and turned into a poſition, to ſee then if we can ſpeed any better. And it will follow thus, or to this effect:</p>
            <p>That true liberty and freedom doth extend further than outward things, as <hi>what I ſhall Eat, and when,</hi> &amp;c. for it reacheth to the things of God, to all that have received the gift of God to profit
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62948:6"/>withall; for ſuch as they do adhere to it, have liberty and freedom in the fear of God, to chuſe what they believe, and are perſwaded is good, and to refuſe, and let alone what they believe and are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded is not good; nor can they act upon another's motion, whilſt they want a ſenſe of it in their own mind, by the gift of God given them to profit withall, but offer a blind Sacrifice to God. Here we hope we have kept cloſe to the true ſenſe of the Queſtion, if affirmed, however we are content to abide by the genuine ſenſe of it according to Truth.</p>
            <p>To this, obſerve he anſwers, this Aſſertion or Queſtion is true in a ſenſe, and that is, he ſaith, <hi>If thou be ſuch an one as is perfectly free to all good, and perfectly free from all evil, then thou may'ſt be ſafely left to thy freedom.</hi> To find whether this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer be full or nay to the Queſtion, we offer, either this Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if affirmed, is true in a larger ſenſe than he has granted, or its but true in this ſenſe.</p>
            <p>If true in a larger ſenſe, it follows, if his aim and deſign, as he ſays, was to aſſert the truth, he has miſſed his mark. <hi>For to aſſert, the truth is ſo comprehenſive a term, as to take in the direct Anſwer to this weighty Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if but true in this ſenſe that he hath laid down, then it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, becauſe I am not arrived at this Perfection he ſpeaks of, that is, to be perfectly free from all that is bad, and perfectly free to all that is good, as Above; though I may have received the gift of God for that end, and do adhere to it, and am travailing for it, yet I am not to be left to my freedom and liberty in the things of God, to act as I am perſwaded. Now if I muſt not act as I am perſwaded, then I muſt act as others are perſwaded; and how I can ſo act and not offer a blind Sacrifice to God, he hath not ſo much as attempted to ſhew which, diſcovers his Anſwer deficient, if his deſign was good.</p>
            <p>Again, either he believes his Anſwer is full to the Queſtion, or he believes and knows it is not: If he believes and knows it is not full, then muſt he not only, not have aſſerted the Truth as above, but alſo be conſcious wherefore he did it not; and we conceive, that muſt either be becauſe he wanted Ability, or otherwiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he wanted Truth in his way, which we ſhall examin by and by.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62948:7"/>
            <p>And in the mean time, if he believed this was a full anſwer to the queſtion, when affirmed, then we muſt aſſert, he was under a great miſtake; for the Queſtion affirmed as above, is certainly not only true in a part, or in a ſenſe, as he is pleaſed to ſay; but it is true in every part, true in the whole, and every ſenſe that a Poſition can be true in; nay it is ſo far true, that if it can be wrong at all, 'tis only in a ſenſe; and that is only when miſ-applied. But the Miſ-application of this weighty Queſtion when affirmed, doth (obſerve) neither deſtroy it in it ſelf, nor in the leaſt take away the true uſe; and therefore we believe, where the gift of God is received to profit withall, and truly adhered too, there muſt be a liberty to chuſe and refuſe things according as ſuch are perſwaded, even from the Babe in Chriſt, to the ſtrong Man, and ſo to all States: Nor do we hereby exclude External Counſel and Advice, but ſtill it muſt accord, and agree with the gift of God received, or 'tis not obliging. And where this is not freely granted, at leaſt among a People that acknowledge the Spirit of Truth to be the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guide into all Truth, there the Government of Chriſt is either directly or indirectly oppoſed or hindered; for admit of one Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror or Uncertainty, and more will follow; an Uncertainty admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the Truth in this caſe, ſtanding in the nature of a Lie.</p>
            <p>But now to ſhew, that this part of his Anſwer which ſeems to affirm the Queſtion, is ſo far from being a direct and full Anſwer, as 'tis not worthy of that name, being of no uſe or ſervice with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Controverſie, the end for which he pleads his great concern to write. For obſerve, though 'tis true in the ſenſe he grants, that thoſe that are perfectly free from all bad, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly free to all good, may ſafely be left to their freedom to act in the things of God as they are perſwaded. Yet, foraſmuch as he neither hath, nor we believe, can give us any certain or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Rule, how to know who theſe are that are ſo to be left; all that he hath ſaid by way of affirming this great and weighty Queſtion, is worth nothing; for as it is altogether unintelligible, 'tis every way impracticable. <hi>Well then,</hi> if any certain Rule can be given to know who may be left to their freedom as above, let us have it, and by the contrary Rule, we ſhall know who may not be ſo left: But if no ſuch Rule can be given, it muſt follow, all muſt be left free, or none muſt be left. If none muſt be left, then muſt an
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62948:7"/>outward Rule be ſet up to govern all, and that would make us like <hi>Iſrael</hi> that rejected God's Government, to be like other Nations. But if all muſt be left free to act in the things of God as they are perſwaded, let all this Clamour ceaſe, that we may be quiet and live like Chriſtians in the fellowſhip of the Goſpel. There is but one Objection, and that is, that this is to give liberty to evil, which we may ſpeak to in another place; and in the mean time, that is far from our thoughts, as the Author ſaid, it ought not to be named among Saints.</p>
            <p>But now to the latter part of his Anſwer, where he makes a flouriſh, as if he would tell us who were not to be left to their free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that ſo he might give ſome thing like an Anſwer to the whole Queſtion; in which, if he ſucceeds no better than he has done above, we believe there is none will be better or wiſer, for what he has done. But to the matter, he tells us, if thou plead'ſt thy freedom againſt ſuch requiſite things, thy freedom is naught, dark, perverſe, and out of the Truth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is ſtill to the ſame tune; here is a Judge implied, but not ſet forth; 'tis not the Spirit of Truth, but ſome outward thing, whatever it is.</p>
            <p>But ſince we know not where he will fix, to ſay no more, 'tis dark to be ſure: To help it all we can, we ſhall thus far grant, there are ſome outward things ſo far eſſential to true Religion, as thoſe that do contrary to them may be detected of Error; but if it had been any of thoſe things that had been done contrary too, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they would not have been omitted here, becauſe if certain, they would have greatly advantaged this Diſcourſe, there being much want of certainty in it: But this not being done, and things laid down in a general way, in which often deceit or cunning lurks, we can do no leſs than judge, that the things ſuggeſted as the ground of Difference, are neither ſuch Principles nor Practices as have been from our beginning, nor yet ſuch things as can be truly ſaid to be eſſential to true Religion; and if not eſſential things, (obſerve it) nor yet ſuch things as have been from our beginning, they can at beſt be but circumſtantial, or if you will, ceremonial or ſhadowy things, and ſuch things at beſt are but accidentally good, that is, as Perſons are perſwaded of them; and what is but accidentally good, may on the contrary, be accidentally not good, and that is as perſons are diſatisfied with them. And if they prove ſuch things as thoſe, we believe they concern only that outward Court which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62948:8"/>God hath left unmeaſured, on purpoſe that Chriſtians might never differ about them; and if ſuch things (as we are fit to take for granted) we would gladly know, how they can be brought in and made terms of Communion againſt the mind of other of the ſame perſwaſion, while we have run down with all our power the like in others? What, was they wrong there, and can they be right here (that's ſtrange) according to truth? But in the likeneſs of truth its not ſtrange, it being commonly found, that Perſons plead for or againſt things in others, which they will neither give nor take themſelves. Beſides it's ſeen, it's about ſuch things that the moſt of Chriſtians have differed, denying Communion to one another on ſome ſpecious pretence or other, forgetting to give what they themſelves deſired to receive. And thus hath poor Man been deceived all along by the Devil in the likeneſs of Truth.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, that the Queſtion above is weighty, we have noted, and that the Anſwer is evaſive, and nothing to the purpoſe, we have ſhewed. The Reaſon wherefore it was evaded, remains to be inquired into according to our promiſe; and that we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſtill as above, muſt either be becauſe our Author wanted A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, or elſe his Cauſe was not good, and ſo could not bear the anſwering it according to truth.</p>
            <p>Not the firſt we are ſatisfied, for thoſe many Tracts wrote by him, when directed to a good end, do abundantly ſhew his Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and skill in things of this kind, yea to that exactneſs, that without flattery, he might have been compared to the Men of <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin</hi> that could hit their Mark to an hairs breadth. Thus it could not be the want of Ability, therefore we are ſatisfied, it was the want of Truth in the deſign carried on; Opinion or the likeneſs of Truth, was endeavoured to be obtruded and ſet up inſtead of Truth; betwixt which and Truth, there is as much difference in the ground, nay, more than betwixt the ſhadow and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; and yet there is that likeneſs in outward appearance, or elſe it could not be called the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity;</hi> by which all are and have been deceived, to their hurt, but only ſuch who are ſincere to God, and cannot ſit down before they know their Names writ in the <hi>Lamb's Book of Life.</hi> This is that only which can fully ſatisfie the <hi>Hungry</hi> and <hi>the Thirsty Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that though Men have begun well, yet if they travel not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62948:8"/>for the end, they muſt miſcarry; for if the Travel ceaſe in any ſtate ſhort of the Reſt, let former Openings and Experiences bin what they will, as that work is ſtopped by the Enemy, ſo are they deceived by him in the likeneſs of the Truth at beſt; for as the Reſt is that which remains for the People of God, ſo is there no ſtate allotted men that have ſimply begun in Spirit to dwell in ſhort of that, becauſe none ſafe but that; the Reſt is only by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Chriſt, the Travel is while he appears in us, to fit us for himſelf, to new create us; for 'tis the new Creature that only finds room in him.</p>
            <p>Now the Enemy, that fallen Angel, can go with Man into every remove, whilſt man is fitting and preparing, but into Chriſt he cannot come; for in him he has no part; upon which account 'tis plain, the difference is great betwixt our being in Chriſt, and he only in us. And as man muſt be made a new Creature before he can come into Chriſt, ſo muſt he travel through the whole Myſtery of Iniquity; and in the laſt ſtep of the Travel, is the very height of the Myſtery known, and not before. Here is the delivering of <hi>Iſaac</hi> up indeed, and the receiving of him again after another ſort: Here the Myſtery is finiſhed, and Man's works ceaſeth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We know whilſt the Hunger and Thirſt remains for God's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in Man's Mind and Soul, he cannot chuſe but be ſincere, and then he muſt travel, becauſe the Hope ſtands before him, and the ſenſe of Eternal Life lives upon his Mind; but if the value of that Heavenly Country fall in his Mind, the Travel ceaſes; and then, if in any ſtate ſhort of the Reſt, 'tis not God nor his Holy Spirit that bears Rule; for where he rules, there is Sincerity, and where there is Sincerity, there's travel. And as the Lord begets it, ſo he has regard to the leaſt meaſure of his own begeting, and there the Enemy is chained, and the Sin of the leaſt Child is forgiven for his Name ſake; ſo that though the Enemy can go with the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he rules not; but if the Travel of the Mind and Soul ceaſe before the Reſt is known, let it be where it will, as the Sincerity ceaſes, it is the Enemy that rules, and the more Knowledge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, the greater is the Myſtery of Iniquity; and when this comes to paſs as there is a falſe Reſt ſet up, ſo there is a great noiſe about outward things. All was quiet before, but now all in a Tumult, not about eſſential, but circumſtantial or ſhadowy things. It would not be ſo, if we truly ſought the Heavenly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62948:9"/>Country, or rightly knew our Lives hid with Chriſt in God; for if that was truly known, firſt, as to the Travel, we ſhould find work enough at Home; and if the latter, wherein our own Works ceaſeth, we ſhould never think of eſtabliſhing God's Kingdom by our Works: But to leave this Digreſſion, and come again to the Matter.</p>
            <p>As the likeneſs of Truth, and Truth, differ in the Ground, ſo their Arguments do alſo differ. Thoſe plain and ſimple Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that will ſerve the Truth, will do nothing for the other to help the likeneſs forward; weighty Queſtions muſt be evaded, or indeed agreeable to the Nature of the matter carried on; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like Anſwer muſt be given to weighty Queſtions, which in truth are none; things that God has left unmeaſured, muſt be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, and a greater value ſet upon them, than he ever ſet; and what ought to be proved, (that it might be certain, becauſe where there wants Certainty there wants Truth) muſt inſtead of being proved, be taken for granted; which begging of the Queſtion is apparent throughout the whole Diſcourſe, as may be ſhewed in part as we proceed; by which 'tis plain to us, and we hope will be to every conſiderate Reader, that the plain tendency of the Paper, was, and is to bring in the likeneſs of Truth, for the Truth, by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring a Conformity that's more preſumptive than real, wherein things muſt be taken for granted, becauſe others ſay it, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they that ſhould receive them, know they are true; and that this Diſcourſe levels at this Mark, is plain to us, and hopes will be to more, if they conſider the go-by to this weighty Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. And this will be further confirmed, when we conſider the Difficulties that lye in the Queſtion, to be anſwered truly, where Mens ways is not that of the Truth.</p>
            <p>To this end conſider, the Queſtion is fair and eaſily anſwered according to Truth; then as his aim was to have aſſerted Truth, he ought to have done it; but 'tis plain with reſpect to Truth and his Diſcourſe, he could do it neither way, that is, he could neither directly affirm or deny the Queſtion.</p>
            <p>For firſt, had he affirmed the Queſtion as he ought to have done, that is to have fairly granted, that where the gift of God is received to profit withall, there all ſuch ought to be left to act in the things of God as they are perſwaded, then had he ſpoyled his Diſcourſe, for he could not deny but thoſe that he would conclude to be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62948:9"/>guided by others, have received the gift of God to profit withall, therefore as this would have been inconſiſtent with his Diſcourſe, 'tis plain, his way was not the way of Truth. Again, had he granted the Queſtion as above, he had not only ſpoyled his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe by aſſerting Truth, but then he had aſſerted and ſtood by one of the Foundations, Principles of our building, and of every true building, to wit, Conviction and Perſwaſion. And indeed without which, as there can be no true buillding, ſo can no true building ſtand where 'tis diſcontinued; this muſt needs have mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Market of thoſe whoſe cauſe he undertook, that cannot be quiet about their Opinions, till others of the ſame Communion are perſwaded, which ought, and muſt be, if Conviction or Perſwaſion muſt preceed Conformity: By Opinions, we mean ſuch things as have not been from our beginning, and which can never be proved eſſential things; for they may tell us, they are moved of God, in the matter, this will not do whilſt we are ſure that he hath left ſuch things on purpoſe unmeaſured, that Men might agree; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, where Perſons will preſs ſuch things to diſſatisfaction, they raiſe themſelves above the level of their Brethren, and then of neceſſity there muſt be ſomething of Lordſhip and Dominion ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, contrary to the Rule laid down by our Lord, who ſaid, after thoſe things the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſeek, but ſaid, it ſhall not be ſo among you; he that will be the greateſt, let him be as him that ſerveth. On this account they was to call no Man Doctor or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that ſo their Dependence might not be on Men, let their Abilities be what they will. And thus, as his Diſcourſe could not bear the affirming truly this weighty Queſtion, becauſe then muſt have granted Conviction; ſo on the other hand, he could not deny it; for had he done that, he muſt have been under an Obligation to have demonſtrated, how there could be a dependance on others in the things of God, without offering a blind Sacrifice to God; but this he could not with reſpect to Truth, and the other he could not, with reſpect to his Diſcourſe; and thoſe we conclude the true Reaſons why the Queſtion was left unanſwered.</p>
            <p>There is one thing more worth our while to conſider before we leave this matter, and that is, how it ſhould come to paſs that a Man of his Ability ſhould ſtate a Queſtion that he could not anſwer, with reſpect to his deſign and end; had another ſet it, and he ſlipt it over, it had been the more tollerable; but for him to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62948:10"/>ſtate it himſelf, and give it the go by ſo ſorrily, is plain weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; to which, what can be ſaid, but when Men will imploy their Parts and Abilities to a wrong end, an end God never deſigned them to, there divine Providence ſuffers Men to ſhew their weakneſs, firſt, that no Fleſh ſhould glory in his Preſence; and ſecondly, that others ſeeing weakneſſes as in the beſt of Men, might be cautioned to wait to know their dependance upon him, that neither ſlumbereth nonſleepeth, nor can be miſtaken, which is all that is deſired by what is writ. We have ſtood the longer upon this, in looking upon its weight.</p>
            <p>He Queſtions Page the 3<hi>d. But muſt I conform to things whether I can receive them or nay? Ought I not to be left to the Grace and Spirit of God in my own Heart?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this, he anſwers to the firſt part of the Queſtion, <hi>Nay;</hi> that is, <hi>Thou ought not to receive things againſt Truth;</hi> to the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part, <hi>Yea;</hi> that is, <hi>Thou ought to be left to the Grace and Spirit of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This is fairly ſaid we muſt confeſs, and if truly ſtood to, might help to make amends for the former deficient An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, but if otherwiſe, it will be a further Evidence his end is not good; and therefore to examin the matter, he ſaith, let us conſider what is the reaſon, that thou canſt not receive them, is the fault in the things, or is it in thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If in thee, thou ought to be dealt with; thus far he hath ſaid well; but now on the other Hand, what if the fault be in the things, or in the ground or manner of bringing them in? What Care has he taken? What Remedy has he provided, that ſuch things may be fairly and freely withſtood? Verily none at all, neither here, nor in any place of his Book that we can find; which certainly he ought to have done, if he had aſſerted equal Liberty according to his Diſcourſe, if it was to aſſert Truth; for he inquires fairly where the fault is, that is, whether in the things brought in, or in thoſe that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not receive them; by which 'tis fairly implyed, if not granted, that the fault may lye on the ſide of the things brought in, as well as on the ſide of thoſe that cannot receive them, and doth lye there for any thing that he has ſaid, to prove the contrary; but if not determined, yet for a much as moſt danger may lye on the ſide of the things, if they muſt come in without controul; for we may conclude, ſuch as bring them in are reputed Leaders; and foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62948:10"/>as the Leaders may do more harm in bringing in things that are wrong, than others can do in oppoſing ſome things that may in ſome ſort be right. But as a way is granted to deal with thoſe that oppoſe what is right, there ought to be as much care for Liberty, to oppoſe what is wrong; but for that he has taken no care, though 'tis plain, the Danger is as great, nay, greater on that ſide; for the Leaders have cauſed the People to err, and the effect was, that the People led by them was devoured. The wiſe Man ſaid, <hi>There was nothing new;</hi> then the Leaders may again cauſe the People to err, and the People may again be devoured for any thing that he has ſaid, either to prove there is no Danger, or by aſſerting true Liberty to prevent it, which can never be better done, nor more according to Truth, than by allowing freely Conviction and Perſwaſion to preceed Conformity; for as this keeps down Men from being maſterly, ſo it helps ſuch as are to receive things, to conſider of true Religion in themſelves; and therefore, the contrary may be the ruin of the whole; on which account 'tis plain, he having taken no care as he hath not aſſerted the Truth, for that allows equal Liberty, ſo he appears partial.</p>
            <p>Again in the ſame Page, he ſays, <hi>It is a dangerous Principle, and pernicious to true Religion;</hi> and which is worſe, he ſaith, <hi>'Tis the root of Ranteriſm to aſſert, that nothing is a Duty incumbent upon thee, but what thou art perſwaded on,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This deſerves our Conſideration, for 'tis as removing a Bounder or Land-mark, 'tis of the ſame Nature with Conviction or Perſwaſion; for if Conviction and Perſwaſion is to preceed or go before Conformity in our Duty to God and true Religion, then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be a Duty incumbent upon us, but what we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded on: But if Duty to God and true Religion muſt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed before convinced or perſwaded to it, then ſomething may be a Duty incumbent upon us, that we know not, or are not perſwaded on.</p>
            <p>We ſhall examine this a little, and therefore offer, if to aſſert or believe that nothing is a Duty incumbent upon us, but what we are perſwaded on, be in it ſelf a dangerous Principle, pernicious to true Religion, and what is ſtill worſe, the root of Ranteriſm, then the ſaying that ſtands againſt this, muſt be as good as that is evil; that is, it muſt be a ſafe Principle, propitious to true Religion; and which is ſtill better, it ſhould be as the root of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62948:11"/>all good to Man; for we conceive, the root of Ranteriſm is as the root of all evil. Well, this ſaying that ſtands againſt the former, is to believe or aſſert, that ſomething is a Duty incumbent upon us, that we know not, or are not perſwaded on; for we muſt either believe, that nothing is a Duty incumbent upon us but what we are perſwaded on, or we muſt believe the contrary.</p>
            <p>Now, as oppoſite ſayings have contrary ſenſes and effects, then if the firſt ſaying be evil, the latter muſt be good; and on the contrary, if the latter in a direct and true ſenſe be wrong, as leading from Truth into blind Obedience, then the former ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, notwithſtanding all his ugly Epithites beſtowed upon it, muſt be good in a true ſenſe, as tending to lead truly to know, both our Duty toward God and true Religion.</p>
            <p>And therefore obſerve, if according to his ſaying, to aſſert or believe that nothing is a Duty incumbent upon us, but what we are perſwaded on, be the root of Ranteriſm worſe than what is pernicious to true Religion: Then to avoid this dangerous Shoal and Sand that he has given notice of, we muſt believe, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is a Duty incumbent upon us that we are not perſwaded on; and if we can thus believe, we muſt of neceſſity depend on him or others, to let us know what our Duty is.</p>
            <p>If this is his meaning, and what he aims at; and for our parts, we can ſee no other ſenſe obvious on the Conſequence of his Argument; we ſay, this muſt be back again to ſomething, like the firſt Covenant that could not make the Commers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto perfect; but this is not ſo good; for that was meaſured of God, whilſt this is not: This is to Impeach the Grace of God, and Spirit of Truth, to whoſe ſufficiency ſo many Teſtimonies have been born, as not now ſufficient to lead all (obſerve) into all Truth; 'tis true, it may imply, that ſome are led into all Truth, or elſe we know not on whom they muſt depend, that are to believe, that ſomething is a Duty incumbent upon them that they are not perſwaded on; but as this is his meaning, he has left us miſerably unprovided, whilſt the Conſequence of his arguing is to make us believe, that ſomething is a Duty incumbent upon us that we do not know, and yet at the ſame time doth not let us know on whom we may depend; but ſeeing our Inability to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand our Duty, muſt be the cauſe of our Dependance, on whom he or others is pleaſed to ſet forth; may not we ſay this bears for <hi>Rome,</hi> where Ignorance is ſaid to be the Mother of Devotion? but that we
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62948:11"/>will not at preſent, becauſe perhaps his meaning may be better than his Expreſſion, and indeed it had been the eaſilier paſſed by, had he made any good Proviſion in his Book, that we might not have been impoſed on contrary to our Underſtandings; but taking no care for that that we can find, as alſo diſcouraging all thoſe Poſitions that ſeems to reſerve a Liberty to underſtand what we are to receive, demonſtrates plainly, the tendency of his writing is to bring in blind Obedience.</p>
            <p>But to confirm his ugly dreſs put upon this ſaying, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is a Duty incumbent upon us but what we are perſwaded on, he tells us, the dead, dark, and ſeared Conſciences plead Liberty againſt all Duty, and this is all that he offers that is material; but this will not do his buſineſs; for there is a vaſt difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt denying all Duty to God, and believing nothing a Duty but what we are perſwaded on: The firſt deny all Duty, the latter owns all Duty that can be known.</p>
            <p>The firſt denying all Duty is directly evil, but the latter, as they own all Duty that they know, ſo may they wait truly to know what God is pleaſed farther to ſhew, wherein a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is included and ſtands; and therefore, for him to joyn this ſtate which may be truly good, with that which is certainly evil, though he has not juſtified the wicked, yet certainly he has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the Righteous, concerning which, there is much might be ſpoken. But in ſhort, either he believes thoſe that believe or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, that nothing is a Duty incumbent upon them, but what they are perſwaded on, are thoſe dead, dark, and ſeared Conſciences, or he doth not ſo believe; if he doth not ſo believe, why doth he compare them with ſuch? But if he doth ſo believe, then ſeeing according to his account, they muſt be dead, dark and ſeared, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they made thoſe Pleas; and then ſeeing there is nothing more contrary to the living than the dead, how came it they was not found out till thoſe Circumſtantial things was brought in? For ſo we muſt account them till they are proved otherwiſe. 'Tis true, he calls them requiſite things, and no marvel that you ſhould ſo eſteem them, when you could not know your dead, dark and ſeared Conſciences without them; but can thoſe requiſite things that keeps out, or makes known thoſe dead, dark and ſeared Conſciences that pleads, being left to the Grace of God, and that nothing is a Duty incumbent upon them, but what they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62948:12"/>on? Can thoſe requiſite things which keeps thoſe above out, keep out Hypocrites? If not, muſt they not be liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or dead Members? If living, we leave you modeſtly to make the Application; but if dead, 'tis worth your while to conſider, if you have not been under ſome miſtake all this time, and ſo have been endeavouring to caſt out the living, but kept the dead; doth this beſpeak you truly living, and your ſpiritual Senſes perfect? To ſay no more to this we doubt not.</p>
            <p>But again, to this Poſition, that nothing is a Duty but what we are perſwaded on; if this ſaying be ſo evil as he has repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, as above, then it muſt be ſo, either becauſe of it's abuſe, or becauſe evil in it ſelf. If it muſt be diſuſed and criminated only becauſe ſome abuſe it, then what is there but it muſt be parted with; according to his own ſaying, Page 4. in a like Caſe, farewell with the Scripture, and indeed with every thing elſe that's good, ſince all thoſe things that Man can meddle with, have been abuſed at one time or other.</p>
            <p>But if he be ſo angry at this Poſition, as evil in it ſelf, which it muſt, if the root of Ranteriſm, then we believe he is in a great miſtake, and do offer in its favour, that what may be ſaid by a Holy and Religious Man; truly as a Holy and Religious Man cannot be Evil, much leſs the root of Ranteriſm, but this, that nothing is a Duty, but what we are perſwaded on, we believe may be truly affirmed by a Holy and Religious Man, and that againſt Impoſition. For as no Man can be Holy but by God's Holy Spirit, ſo no Man can truly know his Duty towards God, but by the ſame Spirit; and as Duty to God cannot be known, nor true Religion performed, but by the Influences of it, ſo we believe where the gift of God is received to profit withall, and truly adhered too, nothing is a Duty incumbent upon ſuch, but what they are perſwaded on. We do not ſay, that nothing ſhall be a Duty but what ſuch are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded on, but this we ſay, whatever ſhall be a Duty, muſt be known before it can be ſo. Now, if nothing be a Duty but what they are perſwaded on, certainly they may affirm on a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian account, nothing is a Duty incumbent upon them, but what they know or are perſwaded on, without being Ranters, which they could not, if this ſaying was the root of Ranteriſm.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:62948:12"/>
            <p>But to obſerve a little what his own Words afford us, he tells us of ſome Perſons above, that was perfectly free from all bad, and perfectly free to all good, which might ſafely be left to their freedom to act in the things of God. Now, we hope however that he will grant, that nothing is a Duty incumbent upon them, but what they are perſwaded on; and then we hope he will allow, they may affirm nothing is a Duty but what they are perſwaded on, and if but true in that one ſenſe, this ſaying cannot be the root of Ranteriſm, for that is true or good in no ſenſe: 'Tis true, he has not given us a Rule to know thoſe of whom we laſt ſpake, nor do we believe that he can ſet them out; but that is not againſt us, but for us; for if any may aſſert, that nothing is a Duty but what they are perſwaded on, tho others may abuſe it, if we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſtinguiſh betwixt the one and the other; he knows Tares muſt be ſuffered to grow, rather than run the hazard to deſtroy Wheat.</p>
            <p>Again, he tells us Page 9. <hi>That a ſaying may be true or falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſubject or matter 'tis applied to.</hi> Now, though we believe he has miſt the truth there, yet it will ſerve us here againſt himſelf; for this Poſition that he is ſo angry at, is but a ſaying, and ſuch as has been advanced truly againſt Impoſition, and again, may be truly uſed on that occaſion; therefore it cannot be the root of Ranteriſm, for that is ſimply evil; wherefore, we hope he will withdraw his Charge of the root of Ranteriſm from this Poſition, that nothing is a Duty incumbent upon us but what we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded on and inſtead of condemning it as evil, allow it as good and neceſſary in its genuine ſenſe.</p>
            <p>But to conclude this matter, we grant a ſaying may come from the root of Ranteriſm, but no ſaying whatever can be that Root, much leſs ſuch a ſaying that hath, and may again be applied to a good end; wherefore we cannot ſee why this ſaying ſhould be written with a different Character for, and this ugly and undeſerved dreſs put on it, except inſtead of perſwading, to affrighten into blind Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>To the latter part of the Queſtion, <hi>Ought I not to be left to the Grace and Spirit of God in my own Heart,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To this he anſwers, <hi>That is of all things most deſirable, for no fear of want of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, where all are ſo left with the one Spirit, they muſt be of one Mind, they cannot be otherwiſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:62948:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> That he deſires all ſhould be guided by God's Spirit, we believe, and therein does well; but that he ſhould limit it to that one way, with reſpect to ſhadowy or circumſtantial things, that he may believe is good, is his miſtake; by which 'tis plain, though he may have received a meaſure of God's Spirit, yet he is not truly born of it, for if he were, he would not limit God's Holy Spirit to this or that ceremonial, circumſtantial or ſhadowy thing; for that is to ſet the meaſure above him from whom it comes, and to meaſure that which God has left unmeaſured, the hurt and miſchief through all the Reformations that have been; this is not the Truth, but a likeneſs of it at beſt, which all hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to have been deceived by, and 'tis our danger. O that it could be conſidered in our day!</p>
            <p>But to the matter, that thoſe that are truly left with the one Spirit of Truth, muſt and will agree, we grant; and therefore, where difference is carried on to the Breach of Charity, one ſide at leaſt muſt be wrong; but which ought in God's fear to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, the greater number cannot determine it; but that there muſt be an Identity of Opinion, as we think the School-men call it, that is a ſameneſs of Mind, and oneneſs of Judgment to circumſtantial, ceremonial or ſhadowy things, is ſooner ſaid than proved, and ſavours more of Curioſity than any real neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>And thus, what he ſeems fairly to grant in the fore-part of his Anſwer above, he takes away in the latter part, by limitting it to an Oneneſs of Mind, or Identity of Opinion, without making a difference betwixt circumſtantial things, and ſuch as are truly eſſential; for though all that fear God, muſt and will agree in the latter, yet there is no neceſſity that they muſt agree in the former; therefore, to inſiſt too much upon ſuch things, have always been of evil Conſequence, making differences greater than elſe they would have been; and the reaſon is plain, for where ſuch things are too much preſſed, 'tis becauſe they are over-valued, and by how much that ſuch things are over-valued, 'tis the likeneſs, and not the truth that prevails; O that it could be conſidered! For by how much, as ſuch things are over-valued, God and his Holy Spirit are neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected. Where this happens, ſuch things that elſe might have been indifferent, becomes ſinful to eſpouſe, by ſuch as truly fear God; for we may note, God and his Holy Spirit can never
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62948:13"/>be over-valued in our Hearts and Minds, but every thing below him may.</p>
            <p>And yet on the other hand, ſome ſeeing this as a certain wrong, the Enemy hath aggravated the matter to make both wrong, and that whilſt they both thought they was right; and thus the Devil hath deceived poor Man, even unto this day; and 'tis our danger, and will continue until the Spirit of the Son of God be more plentifully poured forth upon us that can ſay, <hi>Father forgive them, they know not what they do:</hi> This is that which we want, and ſhould truly wait for, that the great Deceiver, the occaſion of all ſtrife and trouble among ſuch as fear God, might be caſt out, that ſo he might deceive no more; which we hope is near; for there ſeems but one grand Remove to know the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> finiſhed; and that is, to know our Habitation in God who we have profeſſed hath appeared in us by his Light and Spirit: Moſt look for this great <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> every where but where 'tis; they look for it abroad, when it can only be truly finiſhed in their own Hearts; for as he that never knew ſpiritual Bondage, can never know and value true ſpiritual Liberty; ſo he that never knew this great Myſtery of Deceit in his own Mind revealed, can never know a true delivering from it. 'Tis not poſſible to give a Rule by Words to eſcape it; for he that knows the moſt, and thinks by that Knowledge to eſcape being deceived, he is deceived already; we wiſh it could be ſeriouſly conſidered by all, for 'tis the greateſt Tryal Men can meet with. But to make leſſer things than eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial things Terms of Communion, we have obſerved to be a great Evil in others, and ſhall we cry it up as good in our ſelves? That which we have affirmed was never bleſs'd and ſucceſsful in others, ſhall we put in practice? Unity has been the great Plea with which the World hath abounded; and whilſt they have ſought for it in ceremonial and ſhadowy things, inſtead of being united, they have been divided, and inſtead of being gathered, they have been ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, not to the Honour of Chriſt, but the ſhame of Chriſtians; and ſhall we pipe to the ſame Tune for company, in which there ſeems no material Difference, but a change of the Perſons and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions? Have others been determining Truth by the majority of Voices, and do not we ſo too? And if we do, had we not better acknowledge it than let the matter prove it? (Obſerve) do not we ſet up the Body of our Community to determine the matter, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62948:14"/>what difference betwixt that and reſolving matters of Faith by the majority of Voices? For is not the Body taken for the greater number, and then is it not the ſame thing when truly applied; and if this be true, is it not much worſe in us, by how much we begun better? O that it could be conſidered! For otherwiſe we believe, at laſt it will not only be found wrong, but that 'tis but a few that manage this Myſtery, in compariſon to the greater number, though they may be ſupported by their compliance; but as we can truly ſay, <hi>Father forgive them, they know not what they do,</hi> we are not without hope; but ſeeing we have obſerved, that Chriſtians and Chriſtianity was always diſadvantanged by thoſe Pleas for Unity, when put in practice, of which we have had the Experience from others, and now have it among our ſelves, if we could heed to improve the occaſion; and that is, to put in practice among our ſelves that good advice we have given to others, to wit, to make nothing Terms of Communion but eſſential things; to which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that Book ſtyled, <hi>An Addreſs to Proteſtants,</hi> is ſo full to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that if more can be ſaid, no more need, if the Advice there, were but effectually taken by our ſelves, of which to be ſure there's moſt need, that ſo at leaſt, if we cannot mend others, we might prove the truth of our Advice by amending our ſelves; till then, thoſe excellent Precepts want Examples, and all know they're more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing; therefore let us begin to ſet that great and glorious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, which as yet the World never knew. We forbear to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe any part of the Book, conſidering it's great applauſe and late Writing; We hope it ſhould not yet be forgotten. However, it may be reviewed to corroborate the Memory, and then there can want nothing that we know of but Self-application.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, ſince 'tis matter of Fact, that Chriſtians never thrived on a true Chriſtian account, where thoſe Pleas for Unity have been put in practice, relating to ceremonial, circumſtantial, and ſhadowy things; do not object, that was only as carried on to violence; for we ſay, the ground of all Evil is firſt in the Mind, and from a ſtraitneſs there; and therefore, they that omit nothing of that power they have, who can believe, if ſuch had more, they would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy it better? Self-denial and Forbearance is the beſt demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Chriſtian frame of Spirit; for Chriſt did not come to take away the greater Evils only, but the leſſer alſo, yea, even the ground of all ſtrife, that is Evil.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:62948:14"/>
            <p>Therefore let us alter our courſe, and take other but better mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; have Chriſtians and Chriſtianity, as truly ſuch, almoſt been extinguiſhed in the World, by ſeeking an Unity in Opinion? Let us ſeek it in Eſſentials, and then the work is done among us, at leaſt, to peace, and then to be ſure we ſhall promote, according to our power, what the World ſtands need of, as well as to wait, that a true Figure of the Univerſal Church, of which Chriſt is the true Head, may be advanced among our ſelves; and as this is truly ſet up and promoted, all difference dies that's evil, among ſuch as truly fear God; then what remains, will be of no more Evil, than the various forms and colours of Flowers in Gardens, if not of much more ſervice; that true Philoſophers Stone, being known to turn all the Metals into pure Gold. Do we think we have been the moſt true that have been ſince the Apoſtacy, which perhaps we have, as to Notion and Profeſſion of the things of God? Then let us endeavour to promote what is more true. What can hinder the putting this in practice, but the Devil, by the likeneſs of Truth, perſwading this was to give liberty to Evil? And therefore, to prevent that they ſet up their own Works, whereby inſtead of leaving People to come in at the right Door, they do but make them formal. We muſt confeſs this cannot be fully known till God diſcover it, and therefore we muſt wait in Patience for God's time; but 'tis a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake to think, this is to give liberty to Evil, while our end, we are ſure, bears witneſs to the contrary. But to anſwer all the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections that may be made, as it would take up now too much time, ſo perhaps we may not know all that may be advanced; ſo we ſhall omit that till we are better informed of them, as alſo, till more ſitting Opportunity do occur. In the mean time, we deſire thoſe things may be taken in the beſt ſenſe, but if otherwiſe, we hope we ſhall not altogether be unprovided.</p>
            <p>We know 'tis writ, <hi>They ſhall come from the Weſt, North, Eaſt and South, to ſit down with</hi> Abraham, Iſaac <hi>and</hi> Jacob <hi>in the Kingdom;</hi> Thoſe certainly was not of one external Form and Order, as to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial and ſhadowy things, yet we find they agree; but perhaps ſome will ſay, this is in Heaven; well, what then? Muſt they not agree on Earth, that muſt agree in Heaven? Shall not God's Will be done on Earth, as 'tis in Heaven? How elſe ſhall the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this World become the Kingdom of Chriſt, but as the Peace of the one becomes the Peace of the other, and as the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62948:15"/>of that, becomes the Government of this? For is not Chriſt the Head of all that is good, from the leaſt breathing to the fulleſt perfection? And doth not he own all that's of his own begetting, every where, according to the degree of Knowledge revealed? Can any thing that's good in a ſpiritual ſenſe be received, but as it comes down from above? And as Chriſt owns all that is good, ſhall not we own it? Doth not he gather all the good to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one, even himſelf? Doth he gather all univerſally in every Nation that fears him, and work Righteouſneſs without reſpect to ſhadowy things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> wherein they may differ, for thoſe he hath left unmeaſured on purpoſe that they might not hinder? Doth he do this in every Nation, and ſhall not he do it in one Nation? Doth he do this in general, and ſhall he not do it in a Family? Yes, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he will in his own appointed time. 'Tis true, he proceeds by weight and meaſure, nor can we haſten his Work, yet certainly we may wait for it in a true Chriſtian Moderation and Patience, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring the Lord Jeſus may come, and if he pleaſe, quickly to gather the Minds and Spirits of all that fear him in any meaſure, into his Name, that is but one; then would <hi>Sion</hi> become our Solemnity, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a City ſought out, and not forſaken, even the Praile of the whole Earth, not that which is below, for ſhe is in Bondage with her Children; but that which is from above, the Mother of all, that is born free, which is not of Man's Contrivance, Work, or Workmanſhip; for ſhe comes down from above, ready prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of God, for all that is fit to enter therein; Man's Work ceaſeth here; for he can add nothing to her Beauty and Perfection; <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi>'s over Carefulneſs ends here, and <hi>Mary</hi>'s better part is enjoyed, that can never be taken away; and as Man's over-carefulneſs is over here, ſo fear is at an end; for as there is no Night here, ſo her Gates ſtand open by Day, for the good to enter therein, whilſt that which is not good, cannot. The true Church is here indeed, but not yet referable to any Society, with reſpect to outward Rules, and therefore ought to be waited for by all.</p>
            <p>Again, he tells us Page 4. <hi>To plead being left to the Grace of God againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, is to abuſe the very Plea,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> The drift of this Argument is like the reſt, to gain a preſumptive dependance upon Men, either for their greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, or for ſome external conſideration or other, without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> regard to Conviction or Perſwaſion; 'tis true, to plead this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62948:15"/>our Underſtanding is an abuſe of the Plea, and is little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than Hereſie, but none can be an Heretick that truly fears God; therefore, to plead this againſt this or that thing, brought in by this or that Man, or by this or that Aſſembly, that we believe is wrong, is ſo far from abuſing the Plea, that it may be a true uſing of it; therefore, before the Plea is proved abuſed, he muſt prove the things brought in, to concern the Eſſence of true Religion, or thoſe that bring them in, to be infallible, that ſo we may have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is certain to depend on; for as that is a-wanting, Truth is to ſeek till this be done; he doth nothing but beg the Queſtion, we are ſatisfied, and that he knows it.</p>
            <p>Page the 4th. he ſaith, <hi>I muſt ſay unto thee Friend, what if thou wilt not be left unto the Grace and Spirit of God in thy ſelf?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We anſwer readily, then ſuch do the thing that is extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evil; but on the other hand, what if they are left with the Grace and Spirit of God, which they may, or at leaſt ſome, for any thing that he hath ſaid? What Care has he taken? What Remedy has he provided, that true liberty and freedom of Speech may be maintained? Not a word of that, which as it ſhews he has not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted the Truth, for that has no reſpect to Perſons, but allows equal liberty to all, ſo it diſcovers him partially devoted in this buſineſs: He cannot but know equal liberty is abſolutely neceſſary in Truths Government, as alſo, the want of it hath ruined moſt of Chriſtian Societies before us; and as we have heretofore impeached the Building of others as not good, where that was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wanting, allowing it at that time as a main Pillar of our Building, if diſcontinued, our Building that was true, will not only fall down, but then what is ſet up, will be worſe than what has been before us, by how much we did begin better.</p>
            <p>Again in the ſame Page, he asketh, <hi>If he may not exhort to the practice of what he is moved to preſs to the practice of,</hi> &amp;c. If not, he ſaith, <hi>Thou art the Impoſer, by reſtraining me from my Chriſtian liberty, and not only ſo, but away goeth Preaching, and with it, the Scripture, that are both appointed of God for Exhortation, R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>proof and Inſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> We are as much for ſaving of the Scripture as he is, and for ſaving of all that is good; therefore we grant, he may exhort to what he believes he is moved to preſs to the practice of;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62948:16"/>and thus having agreed with him to ſave true liberty, and all that is good, we hope he will accord with us, to ſhut all out that is not good; therefore we ſay, though we have granted this liberty as above, it's not our Duty to obey him, becauſe he ſays it, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we know, or at leaſt are perſwaded, that what he ſays is true; for he may be miſtaken and moved to what is wrong, as well as to what is right, for any thing that we know; and the ſame that may be ſaid to him, is true to every one, and all Men in the things of God.</p>
            <p>Again in the ſame Page he Queſtions, <hi>But are there not various Meaſures, diverſities of Gifts, and ſeveral Offices in the Body?</hi> To this he anſwers, <hi>Yea;</hi> and then queſtions, <hi>But therefore, are not the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of one Mind and Judgment in common and univerſal Matters, relat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Church of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> There is not much doubt in this when truly underſtood, but we are to mind that we be not deceived and impoſed upon, as to what is, or ought to be accounted common and univerſal Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: By common and univerſal Matters, we underſtand, and we hope according to Truth, that is what has been commonly and univerſally received, and not new and novel things that have not been ſo received; for all new things that have not been ſo receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they muſt ſtay that bring them in, whatever they are, till they come in as the former did, to wit, by Conviction, or at leaſt by Perſwaſion, before they can be truly ſaid to be common and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Matters; and in the mean time obſerve, this of Conviction and Perſwaſion preceding Conformity, hath been a common and univerſal matter or thing, becauſe commonly and univerſally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived among us as a great Truth, we believing no true Building could be, or ſtand without it; therefore, let us mind we leave not common and univerſal Matter, and old Truths too, for new Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for if we muſt receive new things for common and univerſal Matters, becauſe ſome that bring them in, call them ſo, would have them ſo, or at beſt, believe they ſhould be ſo, we do not only go from this old received Truth, Conviction and Perſwaſion, the main Pillar of every true Building, but then, what is it that may not be obtruded? This would bring us to reſt upon Opinion, and what is uncertain, then what is more contrary to Truth, and the whole tendency of his Diſcourſe ſeems to this purpoſe, on which account many excellent Truths are miſ-applied.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:62948:16"/>
            <p>Page the 5th, he tells us, <hi>What comes from the Light, Life and Spirit, in one, is the ſame in Truth and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity to the reſt, as if it riſe in themſelves; this is ſeen,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>in our Aſſemblies every day,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> The Deſign of this Argument is to gain a dependance upon the teachings of God, by Inſtruments, equal at leaſt to the teaching of God, immediately by his Spirit, in our own Hearts; but how plauſible ſoever this is, 'tis not according to the Truth, as 'tis in Jeſus; for though there is no contrariety in the Spirit of God, ſo no contradiction in the Spirit teaching, being all for one and the ſame end, to wit, the good of Man, by the Salvation of his Soul; yet betwixt God's teaching by Inſtruments, and teaching immediately by his Spirit in our own Hearts, there is this diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or difference, that the firſt is but to prepare the latter to perfect.; and as the latter is the higheſt Adminiſtration, the Leader being only here, that cannot be removed into a Corner; ſo he is in that Adminiſtration, the ſubſtance of all Types, Figures and Shadows, and the fulfiller of every Addition for Righteouſneſs ſake, to them that truly believe in him; therefore, in a Holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to the Divine Being, we ſay, the teaching of God by his Spirit immediately in our own Hearts, muſt have the preference, if ever we be truly perfected; and yet there is ſo much Truth in what our Author hath ſaid, that when fairly ſtated, we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent it ſhould be as a Rule to meaſure the whole Difference by.</p>
            <p>And therefore we offer, either all that do ſpeak in our Aſſemblies or Meetings, ſpeak from the Light, Life and Spirit, or all do not, if all do ſo ſpeak, ſet it out fairly and prove it, that we may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, but if all do not ſo ſpeak, which we take for granted, then you muſt give us a certain rule to know who do ſo ſpeak and who do not, or otherwiſe you muſt leave us to receive or refuſe, according to the beſt of our underſtanding: Obſerve, we ſay, you muſt either give us a rule as above, or you muſt leave us free, for there doth not appear any mean betwixt thoſe two that can be certain. To make the matter ſhort, we take it for granted, that you can give no ſuch Rule, therefore we conclude, we are left free in thoſe things of God, which when they do come from God's holy Spirit imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, there is no greater Authority, for are then as the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of God.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62948:17"/>
            <p>'Tis true, all ſhould ſpeak thus, but all do not, there's the doubt; and the like doubt is every where, where the Truth is concerned, if not, give us an infallible Rule to know, that the Church as referred to this or that Aſſembly, is infallible; this is abſolutely neceſſary if we muſt not act according to our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; for no leſs than what is infallible, can keep in the Truth. We take it for granted, that you can give no ſuch Rule, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conclude, we are every where free where the Truth is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, to act according to the beſt of our Underſtanding, in the fear of God; for the Truth is but one in all, 'tis not more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many ſay it, nor leſs, becauſe one ſays it; therefore we are as much bound to receive the Truth from one, as from many, and no more to regard many, than one in this caſe; wherefore it follows, as we are not bound to receive from one Man, what he ſaith is Truth, when it agrees not with our Underſtanding, we are not to receive it from many; for it muſt agree with the Underſtanding, or unto ſuch as receives it, it cannot be Truth.</p>
            <p>Again, Truth is to be received for its own value, and not for the value of thoſe that bring it in; for if it were, we were in equal hazard to miſs it on both hands, on the one by an over-value of Perſons, or elſe, how could the Leaders of the People have cauſed to have err'd as they have done? And on the other, by an undervaluing, when God chuſeth the <hi>fooliſh Things of this World to confound the wiſe,</hi> as he often doth; and what is this for, but that <hi>no Fleſh ſhould glory in his Preſence?</hi> Therefore upon this foot, as above, we conclude, that Conviction, or at leaſt Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, muſt be freely allowed to preceed Conformity, as well to keep down that over Greatneſs and Dominion, poor Man by the Enemy's ſubtilty is ſubject to aſpire at, as alſo, to keep every one in mind, that they muſt know the Truth for themſelves, for others can never know it for them; nay, to ſpeak plainly and properly, Truth can only be received for its own value, or it can never be received; ſo that we may ſafely conclude, where Conviction and Perſwaſion are diſallowed, that Government ceaſeth to be true, and is ſo far from being the Government of Truth, as that it wants the likeneſs of it.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:62948:17"/>
            <p>Page the 6th. he ſaith, <hi>They that walk in the Light, have Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip one with another,</hi> 1 John 1. whence he ſaith, <hi>'Tis eaſie to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that thoſe that go out of Fellowſhip, go out of the Light,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Every ſaying or Poſition hath only one other ſaying or Poſition that ſtands againſt it, if therefore what is brought as the Antitheſis, differ from the direct oppoſite ſenſe, the Work that follows, or what is builded upon it, cannot be true.</p>
            <p>Now this Poſition, that they that go out of Fellowſhip go out of the Light, he brings as the true Antitheſis to this Poſition of Scripture, quoted 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. or he doth not ſo bring it; if he doth not bring it as true, he deceivs or abuſes his Reader, but if he do bring it as the true Antitheſis, he is miſtaken; for this is not that true Poſition that ſtands againſt this Scripture; for if it was, then what ſtands againſt this Poſition, would directly be that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, at leaſt in a true ſenſe; for oppoſites remain as fixt in their ſenſe, as the Eaſt doth from the Weſt.</p>
            <p>Therefore, we need go no farther for a Proof of the Truth of the Work, than to take that Poſition that ſtands againſt his; for if it be that Scripture in a true ſenſe, the work is true, but if it prove another thing, then may we ſee the cunning that is in daubing, as well as ſomething of that ground of the falſe reaſoning, that is among the Children of Men.</p>
            <p>To try the matter, his Poſition is, that they that go out of Fellowſhip go out of the Light. Now that ſaying that ſtands a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this, muſt be, that they that keep in Fellowſhip, abide in the Light; this is not that Scripture, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. but another thing, differing materially from it; that Scripture is, <hi>If we walk in the Light, as God is in the Light, then have we Fellowſhip one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son, cleanſeth us from all Sin.</hi> Here the ground and cauſe of true Fellowſhip is a walking in the Light, and the proof that the work is true, is the witneſs in a Man's own mind, by the cleanſing from all ſin without this Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is ineffectual; but where this is, ſuch is ſafe, let what will come; and as this is the beginning and ground of Fellowſhip with God, 'tis the ground of Fellowſhip with thoſe that is born of God; but his Poſition, that thoſe that go out of Fellowſhip, go out of the Light, make Fellowſhip with Men (for ſo it muſt be underſtood at laſt, or 'tis un-intelligible) to be the ground of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62948:18"/>Fellowſhip with God, or of walking in the Light, as God is in the Light, which is the ſame thing; and as for the Proof that the work is true, to wit, the cleanſing from all ſin, not a word of that, ſhould the witneſs in a Man's ſelf been ſpoken on, or referred too, all his work had been to no purpoſe, grant that, and no hopes of conforming before Conviction; from hence 'tis plain, 'tis Form, and not Power and Life, that is ſo ſtrenuouſly endeavoured to be ſet up.</p>
            <p>But the ſenſe and conſequence of his Argument ſets Fellowſhip up inſtead of Truth; for we can find no difference by his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, betwixt ſaying, <hi>They that go out of the Truth, go out of the Light, and they that go out of Fellowſhip, go out of the Light;</hi> but as the word <hi>Fellowſhip</hi> is ſet up for Truth, we muſt inquire what muſt be underſtood by it; for it cannot ſtand of it ſelf. Therefore to make it intelligible in the beſt ſenſe, we muſt joyn to it what he calls the Church, and then that Church muſt relate to People, and at laſt we judge, it muſt relate to thoſe Orders, Rules and Forms, that are ſet up by this Church; for the difference begun there, and therefore the Fellowſhip ſeems to ſtand there: and then according to the Conſequence of his reaſoning, in our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, his Poſition muſt be read thus, or to this effect; <hi>They that go out of Fellowſhip with this Church, in theſe circumſtantial or cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial things, which ſhe ſet up to be obſerved, they go out of the Light that God dwells in:</hi> Now, if this be true, the contrary Poſition is as true; <hi>That they that walk in Fellowſhip with this Church, in the things ſhe ſets up to be obſerved, they abide in the Light that God dwells in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the whole, 'tis neceſſary to know, whether all this be true or nay; if not neceſſary, a bare Conformity will ſerve, and they that can believe this Doctrin, have no more to do but to mind to keep in Fellowſhip with this Church, in the things ſhe ſet up to be obſerved; and what may confirm ſuch in it, is his Poſition, <hi>That they that go out of Fellowſhip, go out of the Light;</hi> for if this be certain, the contrary is as certain, <hi>That they that keep in Fellowſhip abide in the Light;</hi> but if needful to know the truth of thoſe things beyond a bare Conformity, Belief or Report, as moſt ſure it is; for if we muſt be led by this Church, and ſhe be wrong, and that not known, our Damage is irreparable; but if ſhe is right, 'tis as neceſſary to know that, as it was the other, otherwiſe we may
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62948:18"/>be wrong, whilſt ſhe may be right. Now, whether ſhe is right or wrong, can only be truly known by coming ſincerely to the Spirit of Truth in our own Hearts, and there waiting to know what is right, and what is wrong; for that way only can we be gathered into the Truth, and kept out of what is wrong; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt affirm, 'tis abſolutely neceſſary for every one to come to the Spirit of Truth for themſelves, for he that knoweth not the Truth in himſelf, can never know it in another as he ought to know it, nor can he value the Truth in another, that doth not firſt love and value it in himſelf; by which 'tis plain, 'tis God that adds to the true Church, and not Man, though we do not deny any means that God may make uſe of; but as they all direct to him, ſo they all end in him, for <hi>Righteouſneſs ſake to them that tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to come to his Argument again, which is, that 'tis eaſie to conclude, <hi>That thoſe that go out of Fellowſhip go out of the Light;</hi> to which we ſay, as eaſie as it is, 'tis not ſafe; ſo to conclude upon this Argument, the Word <hi>Fellowſhip</hi> being dubious and uncertain, as above, becauſe thoſe that did go out of Fellowſhip with the Apoſtles, did go out of the Light; therefore, thoſe that go out of Fellowſhip, or differ with this or that Aſſembly, in this or that ceremonial or ſhadowy thing, go out of the Light, is no good Argument, being ſtill but a begging of the Queſtion; what is this but to over-value our ſelves, and bear witneſs of our ſelves as others before us have done, endeavouring to ſet our Poſt by the Apoſtles, which we cannot? And if we could, the work would not follow God hath deſigned, which is to go forward; but inſtead of that, there would be a declining, ſeeing 'tis plain, as the Apoſtle and theſe then were moſt eminent, ſo there was a declining until the true Church did go into the Wilderneſs; nor can the work ſucceed better, whilſt thoſe that go before are to be relled on in the things of God, or whilſt they look for it betwixt the Apoſtles time, and the Church going into the Wildernſs; the inquiry was, what the Apoſtle did thinking by doing what they did, to meet with the ſame Life and Power, or at leaſt by doing ſuch things to find acceptance with God; but when that was miſſed, and Life could not be found, nor Satisfaction in obſerving of outward things, then was the true Church allured by the Lord into the Wilderneſs ſtate, wherein nothing could ſerve to ſatisfie the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62948:19"/>Immortal Soul, but what came immediately from God, and then ſuch God viſited by his Holy Spirit, according to their ſtate and his time, and ſo from ſtep to ſtep, till he came to us, to whom we believe he hath appeared more clearly than to any ſince the Apoſtacy; and as we have ſeen that Chriſt muſt be the beloved of the Soul, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we could by his Holy Spirit be led out of the Wilderneſs, ſo it muſt be a true dependance upon him that can only perfect that Work begun, according to his own will; and as we believe there is to be no end of the increaſe of his Government now begun, we are to conſider there is ſome alteration in the work; it then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, it muſt now increaſe, and if it muſt increaſe, we may well conſider, as God is Infinite and Eternal, he hath ſtill more Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Power, and Glory to reveal; and as we think of this, and conſider that we are but come to the beginning of this glorious Day, we ſhould be ſo far from thinking our ſelves the greateſt, as we ſhould think our ſelves the leaſt; for this only fits Men to know more, this is that which makes the Elders low and little in their own eyes, and then always ready to throw down their Crowns at the feet of Jeſus, let him appear when, how, and where he pleaſes. Thus there muſt be a looking forward, and not backward for the mind of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This hath yet never been truly known in any Reformation; for inſtead of waiting truly upon him that ſtired in their minds, and ſhewed them things that was true, and did appear to them in the uſe of outward things, whilſt their mind was ſincere to him, we ſay, inſtead of waiting upon him to compleat and fulfil thoſe Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions that might be ſerviceable for a time, they depended too much on outward Things, and limited him by thoſe Forms that he had appeared in; and herein the Elders in every breaking forth of God ſince the Apoſtacy, have not been the leaſt to blame, and the ſame Rocks or like them on which they were ſplit, is our dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; wherefore, we ſhould not think by what we know, to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure what is to come, or that the form that is now ſet up, is that which the People of God for the future are to be found in, for as that may, and certainly will make us miſs of the appearance of the Lord that is ſtill to come, ſo do we hereby limit the Holy one as much as is in our power, and ſuch may as juſtly be reproved as they was of old, to whom the Lord ſaid by his Prophet, <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is my Throne, and the Earth is my Footſtool; where is the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62948:19"/>Houſe that you will build for me, or where is the place of my Reſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 6. he asketh, <hi>If there be not a Chriſtian Body, and whether this Body hath not a Head, and whether Chriſt be not this Head, and whether this Head be without Eyes, Ears, Smell and Taſte, and this Body without Senſe and Feeling; if not, whether this Head beareth, ſmelleth, ſeeth, taſteth differingly, and contrary to it ſelf; and whether this Body hath a contrary feeling at the ſame time, about the ſame thing; and if it be true, that the Church of Chriſt redeemed by his moſt precious Blood, to live to him; ſee with the ſame Eye, hear with the ſame Ear, ſpeak with the ſame Mouth, live by the ſame Breath, and are led by the ſame Spirit, where is this Diſagreement, Contrariety, or diſſent about the things of his Church?</hi> We ſhall ſubjoin part of Page 8, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them together. <hi>They that have Chriſt for their head, have one Counceller, they diſagree not in their Judgments in things relating to Chriſt and good of his Church, they have one and the ſame guide,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Now to every Member is a Meaſure of the ſame Spirit given to profit with u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and though every Member is not an Eye, nor an Ear, nor a Mouth, yet every Member hath unity with the Eye, with the Ear, and with the Mouth, in their proper and reſpective Acts, and they one with another: The Eye ſees for the Mouth, and the Mouth ſpeaks for the Eye, and the Ear hears for both,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>it muſt be granted, that there are helps in the Church as well as that there is a Church at all; and the holy Ghoſt has compared thoſe helps to ſeveral Members and Senſes of a Man's Body, as an Eye, an Hand, a Foot, Hearing, Smelling,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>all then cannot be the Eye, neither can all be the Hand, for then they would confound their Offices; and if I will not comply with him that is made an Eye, becauſe I am not that Eye, or an Hand, becauſe I am not that Member my ſelf, nor a Party to the Action or Performance of that Member, I reſist the Lord, though under pretence of reſisting Man for the Lord's Sake,</hi> &amp;c. with much more to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The moſt of all this is in the way of queries, but in ſhort, ſomething or nothing muſt be intended by them; if nothing, they're vain and to no purpoſe; if ſomething, 'tis plain 'tis to gain a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon what he calls the Church, and that he makes infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as ſhe relates to Men, that ſhe muſt relate to Men is clear the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference being betwixt Men and Men, that he intends her infallible is alſo clear if he writes his Mind; for as he makes no proviſion in all his Book to the contrary, by allowing Conviction to preceed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62948:20"/>to her Orders, ſo alſo he ſeems to make her immediately joyned to Chriſt for her Head, as the natural Body is joyned to the natural Head; to ſpeak a little to all this, which might be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of many and large Diſcourſes; firſt it doth not ſeem to hang well together; in the firſt part he tells us, this Church hears with the ſame Ear, ſees with the ſame Eye, and ſpeaks with the ſame Mouth; in the latter part, that Members of this Church, except he means another Church, are made an Ear, an Eye, a Hand, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as may be ſeen plainly above; is not this inconſiſtent? In the firſt they all ſeem to hear for themſelves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the latter, ſome hear immediately, and ſome ſecondarily; the firſt hear immediately, not only for themſelves, but for others alſo; the ſecond hear only for themſelves by others; is this to hear with the ſame Ear, ſee with the ſame Eye? we doubt not, but if it be, to ſay no more to this, we deſire it may be better explained.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, as to the Church that is perfectly redeemed by the moſt precious Blood of Chriſt, to be <hi>Bone of his Bone,</hi> and <hi>Fleſh of his Fleſh,</hi> and ſo united to him as the natural Body is to the natural Head, we grant it may be ſaid in a good ſenſe, that ſhe ſees with the ſame Eye, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but this is that Church that is hid from the World, as Chriſt is hid from the World; yet he knows who are his, and they know him and his Voice. All ſhould travel for this, and not fit down contented in any thing, till they know the white Stone where the new name is writ, that none can know ſo well as them that have it; and though the Bride, the Lamb's Wife, in this ſenſe is making her ſelf ready to do the Father's Will, yet we find not that this Church hath ſhewed her ſelf unto the World, or that ſhe may thus ſhew her ſelf we cannot determine; for her Life is hid with Chriſt in God, but if ſhe have or may be known by any infallible Character; that ſo what is, or may be ſaid of this Church, that is truly in God, in which there is neither ſpot nor wrinkle, may be truly applied to any viſible Society; let him then ſet her forth as a City on a Hill, that ſhe may not be hid, which he ought to do, if there muſt be that dependance which his Writings imply.</p>
            <p>And then let us know, what Member is this Eye, that we muſt ſee by, and what Member is this Ear that we muſt hear by, and what Member is this Mouth that we muſt ſpeak by, in thoſe things that relate to Chriſt and his Church, that ſo we may not be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62948:20"/>upon by ſuch as may pretend to be that Eye, that Ear and Mouth, and are not; for if this be the Ordinance of God, it both may, and ought to be done; for God yet never deſigned an end with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Man, but he diſcovered the means: Therefore let us have what is certain, or we cannot have Truth. Will he have us to depend, and not certainly tell us what on? He doth not intend that ſure, for that would be to bring in as great a Chimera on a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious ſcore, as we have ever heard of, when this is conſidered; if this can be done that is inſiſted on above, let it be done, that ſo difference may come to an end; but if this cannot be done, then that we may be quiet, let all concerned conſider, there is that to be done they yet cannot do, that ſo in a ſenſe of our Nothingneſs and Inability, we may wait on him that's able to do all things; and in the mean time let us conſider, if it hath not been on this foot, that all before us ſince the Apoſtacy have miſcarried, haſting God's work, taking that to themſelves, God has not yet given to any viſible Society, if ſo we can only avoid that Rock by being more humble.</p>
            <p>And therefore we deſire ſuch as do know what he means, and take themſelves of this Church, to conſider ſeriouſly in their own minds, if they find themſelves thus qualified to take the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt upon their Shoulders, that ſo others may cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly depend on them in the things of God, as infallible; and if they do not thus find it, then to conſider, if they certainly know who are thus qualified, on whom, not only themſelves, but others alſo may depend: But if this be not known, then whether they are ſtill to ſuppoſe, that there is ſome that are thus qualified, and on that Suppoſition preſumingly depend, ſeeing where there wants Certainty, there muſt want Truth. This we commend to every ones ſerious Conſideration, for the good of their own Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Souls, that they may not depend on Suppoſitions, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures, or at beſt, but on Probabilities, but that all may be eſtabliſhed on God's everlaſting Truth, manifeſted in their own Souls, the Truth of all Shadows, and that which fulfils all Additions for Righteouſneſs ſake.</p>
            <p>But again, what doth he drive at? What doth he intend by placing Infallibility upon this Church, as it relates to Men? To us, it muſt either be to ſet up the worſhip of God, or not, if not, we cannot find 'tis worth his while; for if God's worſhip may be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62948:21"/>known without their being ſet up, as infallible, there can be but little, if any thing at all in it; for where God's worſhip is truly known, ſuch muſt love God with all their Hearts, and who ſo loves God, cannot avoid loving his Neighbour as himſelf; and herein the whole Duty of Man ſeems included.</p>
            <p>But if any think the worſhip of God cannot be ſet up, but as direction comes from Men, called a Church, and that becauſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can ſet up the worſhip of God, but what is infallible, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt accept the Church as infallible in this matter; then we enquire if this be not to have two infallible Rules for one and the ſame thing, for the Spirit of Truth is certainly one infallible Rule, and if this Church be another, then here's two; but as this is improper, ſo they cannot both ſtand together. However, we may diſtinguiſh the one from the other, the one is to be look'd for in the mind, the other from Men, called a Church without, and ſo the one is inward, the other outward, but taking this in the beſt ſenſe, not as meer Men, but as they think, Men indewed with God's Spirit, and thereby fitted for Government.</p>
            <p>Now which of thoſe muſt give way, for both cannot ſtand in equal Authority together, will any venture to ſay, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward muſt give way, for a few, or the leſſer number cannot be ſo ſuch as many, or the greater number, however, not as this Church that is ſet up as the Ground and Pillar of Truth, then we deſire ſuch to conſider, if they do not juſtle Chriſt out of his Throne, or at leaſt, ſet up a Tutor or Governour over the Spirit of Truth, as ſome before us have done, who begun well, and will ſtill in the general, in a good meaſure acknowledge, as we do to the Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of God's holy Spirit; but then they tell us, the Scripture is the Rule, and what difference is there to tell us the Church is the Rule; the Heir while under Tutors and Governours, differing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from a Servant, though he be Lord of all. We would by no means miſs your meaning, either you take your ſelves as infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the matter, or not, if not, we ſay, why do you impoſe upon your Brethren? For if you're not infallible, certainly you muſt allow Conviction to preceed Conformity, but if you think your ſelves infallible, we tell you, notwithſtanding that you are to give way, for we hope all will conclude our Saviour perfect, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way infallible, and as good, and as certain a Rule as any Church can be, while he was in that Body prepared for him; and if his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62948:21"/>Diſciples could not be made perfect, while he ſo abode with them, we hope no Church will take more to themſelves, or think they can do more than he did. Well then, if you will ſeek his Will, as he ſought or did the Father's Will, you muſt do as he did, you muſt tell your Diſciples or thoſe that depend upon you, that you muſt go away as a guide to them in the worſhip of God, and a holy Converſation, before they can be made perfect; for it is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as expedient for you to let all know, how far your Miniſtry can go, as it was for him; did he tell his Diſciples it was expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for him to go away, or elſe the Comforter could not come, the Spirit of Truth, that only guide into all Truth? 'Tis as expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, we are ſure for you, to let all know, that except Men come into their own minds, and there wait to know the work and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God for themſelves, they can never be made perfect by your Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>We would not have you miſtake us, do we hereby make void the gifts of God given unto Men for the work of the Miniſtry? No, by no means; but we would have all to know, that the beſt of gifts for this end, are but Additions, and are not to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuated as for ever, for that which is but until, hath a limit, and ends in him that gave them; and as all ought to look for Chriſt the hope of Glory, to ariſe in their minds to fulfil every Addition, ſo ſhould all that have received any gift from God, direct all to him, in whom they all end, otherwiſe ſuch will be always learning, but can never know that Truth that maketh free; for though the light of a Candle is good, 'tis in the dark, 'tis in the Night, and they that uſe it are ſenſible of its ſervice, yet in in its uſe wait for the Day to come, for the Sun to ariſe, where its ſervice is ſwallowed up and truly fulfilled; even ſo the light that comes from Men, as it comes from God to them, is good and ſerviceable by way of direction, but its chief ſervice is to thoſe that are in the dark; and therefore, if the Son of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs be not waited for through the uſe of it, to riſe upon their Souls, they ſtill remain in the dark, notwithſtanding all the teaching of Men, let their Gifts and Abilities be what they will; therefore ſend all to Chriſt, and leave all with him, ſeek his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour truly, and he will certainly ſeek yours, otherwiſe not.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:62948:22"/>
            <p>He Queſt. Page 6, and 7. <hi>But the Members of Chriſt's Church in the Primitives, had different apprehenſion as the Apoſtle and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple gathered by them:</hi> To this he anſwers, <hi>Pray let me know who they were, and in what caſes, the Perſon was</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Peter, <hi>and thoſe Christians that differed about Meats?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> As to that difference betwixt <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it was more the Author's own ſtating, than any bodies elſe, except ſome might bring it to beat down that over-value, which Men are ready to take to themſelves, becauſe of their Elderſhip or Priority, conſidering that here an elder Apoſtle was corrected by a younger, though the beſt of it is, he bore it well for any thing that we hear.</p>
            <p>As to that of Meats, it is true, 'tis an inſtance of weakneſs, but that doth not conclude them weak that made the Objection, but rather ſtrong, that was contented to be accounted weak rather than you ſhould be unquiet; but whether weak or ſtrong, ſeeing we are ſure, there are ſome that is conſcienciouſly diſſatisfied, you ought to hear or forbear, and ſo avoid, or provide for the cure of Diſſatisfaction and Diviſion. But to that of Meats, he has unfairly avoided the weight of the Objection, by omitting days; 'tis true, he has an <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but his Anſwer is as foreign to it, as if no ſuch thing had been.</p>
            <p>As to Meats he pleaſed to ſay, <hi>It did not concern Church-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, but was private and perſonal Freedom, and centered here, as what I will eat, and when, as a Man having power over his own Appetite;</hi> when 'tis plain from Scripture, they were not free, but bound on the account of Conſcience; however, we hope he will not ſay they obſerved days too, under the ſame notion, but if he will, to make way for blind Obedience, who can help it? However, 'tis plain from <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. that the Church at <hi>Rome,</hi> or ſome emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently concerned therein, took things under another notion, tho' wrong too, as all have been ſince, that have made circumſtantial things Terms of Communion, or how comes it that the Apoſtle bids them receive ſuch? By which 'tis plain, either that ſuch had been rejected, or could not be received on thoſe Terms, ſo that the Objection if fairly ſtated, is valid; and thus far to the caſe in hand, as to prove various Practices in ſuch things, tollerated by an Apoſtle, though contrary to a Churches mind, or ſome emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently concerned therein, and if various Practices then in Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantials,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62948:22"/>why not now? To ſay thoſe then did not concern Church-Communion, but thoſe now do, is to make the Church now, or ſome eminently concerned therein, the Author of Schiſm or Diſſatisfaction, as ſhe or they was then, the only difference that we can find, they could not then be admitted, becauſe they ſtuck too much to Circumſtantials; and now ſome are thruſt out or rejected, becauſe they cannot receive ſuch like things.</p>
            <p>But that we may accept of thoſe things in queſtion, whatever they are, he tells us, <hi>They are not Jewiſh Rites;</hi> doth it therefore follow, they are no Rites, or becauſe not Jewiſh Rites, they ought to be accepted as Chriſtian Rites? But further, as he tells us they are not <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Rites, ſo he tells us, nor ſhadowy Ceremonies; doth he mean they are no ſhadowy Ceremonies, becauſe not Jewiſh, or becauſe in Chriſt's Government at laſt there is none? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he would not have thoſe received as ſuch, but if not ſhadowy Ceremonies, pray let us know what they are.</p>
            <p>For if not ceremonial or circumſtantial, they muſt be eſſential, and if not ſhadowy, they muſt be ſubſtance; cannot Men be true Chriſtians without them, or cannot Mens Lives and Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be ſuch as adorn the Goſpel, if they want them? If not, we muſt confeſs, they are eſſential, otherwiſe they are but ceremonial or circumſtantial when all is done.</p>
            <p>Again, will thoſe things he ſpeaks of lead into all Truth, thoſe that obſerve them, or at beſt, but into ſome things that is true? If into all Truth, then we muſt acknowledge they're ſubſtance, but if but into ſome things that is true, they're but ſhadowy: We find the great hurt and miſchief among Chriſtians is a miſtake, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving becauſe Chriſt came to end the ſhadowy ceremonies of the firſt Covenant to the <hi>Jews,</hi> therefore as there ſhould be none in Chriſt's Government, ſo there is none, and ſo under this miſtake, contend for ſuch Rules and Forms as they have, not as ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, but as eſſential things; while the contrary is plain, for the beſt of outward Means, Rules and Forms, as they direct unto God's worſhip, and unto Communion and Fellowſhip with him, are but ſhadows; for they muſt be ſubſtance or ſhadow as above; if ſubſtance, they lead into all Truth, if ſhadows, but into ſome things that is true. The ſubſtance is God's Holy Spirit, that only and alone guides into all Truth, the outward rule, the ſhadow; in Chriſt there is no ſhadow, and therefore all that are in him,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62948:23"/>though they may do the ſame thing the ſhadow leads to, yet they do it not by an outward Rule, but by his immediate Government; they do it naturally by participating of the Divine Nature, Chriſt being truly, not only the object of their mind, but the whole Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Mind and Soul is immediately upon his Shoulder, one Spirit with him, by being joyned to him, where every Addition is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled for Righteouſneſs ſake; but ſuch as are under the ſhadow, though Chriſt be their end, yet the ſhadow is the object of their Mind, thinking to find Chriſt in this or that Duty, or ſerve him in this or that thing; and though every thing that is obſerved for a good end, is ſerviceable, if that end be looked for through the uſe of the outward things, but if a ſitting down in the outward Court, then it will not only be a ſhadow, but become a vail and a ſnare, as well as the abuſe of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law did unto the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page the <hi>9th.</hi> he ſaith, <hi>'Tis true, the People of God ought to be left to the guidance of the Spirit of God in themſelves,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is as fair as a Man can ſay, but hitherto through-out his Book, what he gives with one Hand, he takes away with the other; for he proceeds and ſays, <hi>For this to be ſo applied, as to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regard the Preachings and Writings of Chriſt's inlightned Servants, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by them properly applied to the Preaching and Writing of falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Seducers, will by no means follow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> We are of his mind in this, and do ſay ſo too; but this is but a beging of the Queſtion, who are thoſe Servants, and what are thoſe Writings that are true, that are rejected? We grant readily, to apply this, and ſuch like ſayings as this, <hi>That I muſt mind the Spirit of God in my ſelf,</hi> &amp;c. only becauſe others have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied them, or againſt ſuch as we believe are Chriſt's inlightned Servants in the things that we believe they are inlightned in, or to apply them to avoid the Croſs of Chriſt in our ſelves, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly evil; but to apply them againſt what we believe is wrong, and impoſed, let who will be concerned, may be a true Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; for the like cauſe will have the like effect, where-ever it appears.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But he proceeds,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>the Doctrin is true, but not excluſively of all External Counſel,</hi> &amp;c. We ſay ſo too, for we are for agreeing with him as far as we can; and therefore, that we may continue, we muſt mind him, there is a vaſt difference betwixt excluding all
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62948:23"/>External Counſel, and receiving all for Counſel, that comes from this or that Man, or from this or that Aſſembly; and we are ſure we cannot find that he makes any good proviſion in his Book to the contrary, by allowing Conviction to preceed Conformity; but he ſaith, ſuch ſayings as this, that <hi>I muſt mind the Spirit of God in myſelf,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are falſe in Application, where Men are allowed (obſerve) to have had the fear of God, and mind of his Spirit, and are not proved to have acted in their own Wills,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> We did concur above as far as we could, but now we muſt diſſent; it is not therefore falſe in Application, for that were to ſay, becauſe ſome have had the fear of God and mind of his Spirit, therefore ſuch have it now, or always. Again, becauſe ſome are not proved to have acted in their own wills, therefore ſuch have acted in the will of God, and therefore we muſt depend on ſuch at all times, in what they direct, becauſe we believed that once they was right. O ſad Argument! How is it poſſible that we ſhould believe his cauſe good, when we are ſure thoſe are unſound Arguments; and are alſo certain, the Truth ſtands in no need of what is untrue to defend it, much leſs can make uſe of what is falſe, nay, that belong to what is wrong, or at beſt to what is but like Truth; and to this purpoſe is the whole Page, nay the whole Book; for inſtead of proving things, he takes for granted, that this Church muſt be right, and all ſhe differs with muſt be wrong; but the miſchief is, we know not certainly what he means by this Church, and therefore deſires ſhe may be ſet forth fairly; and in the mean time we believe, he can no more prove her infallible as directed to Men, than he can make this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument good, that becauſe ſome had the fear of God as above, therefore ſuch have it now; wherein there is no Evidence, no Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty to depend on; for ſuch may have had the fear of God, and mind of his Spirit, and for all that, may now be without it as well as himſelf, who uſed to have good Arguments, but now wants them.</p>
            <p>Again, every Fact muſt be committed before proved, therefore they may have acted in their own will, and not yet fully proved; but what proof would he have, and we will endeavour to provide; in the mean time, can any indifferent Man think that all this Smoak can be without Fire? What, one part all right, and t'other all wrong; let them think ſo that can, we cannot, and not only
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62948:24"/>ſo, but if we have allowed any to have had the fear of God, and mind of his Spirit in things offered to us, if that allowance was true, (obſerve) it was becauſe we had a divine ſenſe, relliſh, and taſte of it in our own Hearts; was not this all the true Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence we had, or could have, that ſuch was right? And are we to go any further for a proof, that ſuch are wrong, then when the ſame Evidence comes not along with them? Nay, inſtead of that Evidence, what we have is either againſt the things, or manner of bringing them in, muſt not we ſtand or fall here, or otherwiſe put our own Eyes out on purpoſe to be led and guided by others, and that before we are either perſwaded, that their ſight is good, or deputed to lead us?</p>
            <p>Page 11. he ſaith, <hi>The Enemy is at work to ſcatter the mind of Friends, by thoſe looſe Pleas as leave me to my freedom, and to the Grace of God in my ſelf,</hi> &amp;c. For he ſaith, <hi>The plain Conſequence is to go from ancient Principles and Practices, as there ſet down, and to ſet mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure againſt meaſure,</hi> as in Page 12. which he ſaith, <hi>is Confuſion it ſelf,</hi> Babel <hi>indeed; this is the very Rock,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>both Profeſſor and Prophane would long ſince have run us upon; that a way is hereby opened to all the World, Libertines to plead the light within, for their Exceſſes,</hi> &amp;c. which he ſaith, <hi>grieveth God's Spirit, and was ſeverely reproved by our Friends in the beginning, and is ſtill reproved by them that keep their Habitation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The ground of this great noiſe and clamour, was not a going from ancient Principles or Practices, but your bringing in new things, and preſſing them to diſſatisfaction, againſt which it was alledged by thoſe diſſatisfied, as the Spirit of Truth was not only allowed, but was truly the only guide into all Truth, they ought to be left to the Grace of God in this matter, and not preſſed to receive circumſtantial or ſhadowy things, contrary to their free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and ſatisfaction; here ſuch pleaded Conſcience againſt Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. Now, will you for this, criminate ſuch with going into what is evil or immoral, or at leaſt with deſigning ſuch things; is not this to judge before the time? What's this, but firſt to ſuſpect your Brethren of evil, and then kill them in a ſenſe, to prevent it, a practice always judged by us in others, as evil and unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and therefore every appearance of it ought to be avoided in our ſelves; do ſuch, or did they meet together? And then as a Church, agree what Rules ſhould be obſerved by you, and might
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62948:24"/>not they do that as well as you? For if Church Authority may be pleaded in the caſe, a few may be a Church as well as many; for 'tis not the greatneſs of the number in a Scripture ſenſe, but the qualifications of the Perſons that makes a true Church.</p>
            <p>But if nothing that is ſimply evil or immoral, can be charged upon your Brethren, nor yet any exceſs in impoſing new things upon you, will you to make way for Lordſhip and Dominion over your Brethren, joyn with the prophane, and Profeſſors againſt them and the Truth, or at leaſt, againſt thoſe Teſtimonies to it? For when he tells us, <hi>That this was the very Rock, Profeſſors and Prophane would have run us upon, namely, that hereby a way was opened to all the Worlds Libertines, to plead the Light within for their exceſſes;</hi> either he makes ſome Friends, among which is himſelf, to be one with Profeſſors againſt the light within, or otherwiſe, doth not he joyn what is unequal together? For it is plain, that the Profeſſors, tho' they owned the light within, and Spirit of God in a ſenſe, yet they denied, it was a ſufficient Rule to be relied upon, to guide into all Truth, and gave this for a reaſon, as it was an inward and hidden Rule, if allowed ſufficient, as Independent to any outward Rule, then it opened a way for the Worlds Libertines to plead the light within, for their exceſſes; and thus, though they owned the light within, and Spirit of God in a ſenſe, yet they ſet up the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as ſuperiour, and guide unto it, and do not you in effect the ſame thing? For though you do not ſet up the Scriptures, yet both by the management of things, and the tendency of our Author's diſcourſe, you ſet up the Church as a Rule and Guide to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Light within, and what difference is there, ſeeing both have equally been miſapplied by the cunning, crafty reaſonings of Men?</p>
            <p>Now conſider, is there any cauſe for all this noiſe, ſave your Brethren pleading the light within, againſt your forcing new things upon them? 'Tis true, he ſaith, <hi>This Plea is a Deviation from the ancient Teſtimony;</hi> but how doth he prove it? For forcing circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial, ceremonial or ſhadowy things, is of the ſame nature with the impoſing of ſuch like things by others; the difference of the the thing or Perſons, do not alter the nature of Impoſition. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is Impoſition ſtill, ſo that if you impoſe, it will be the ſame thing; and you muſt either impoſe or not; if you deny that you impoſe, why are not you quiet? But if you own that you do
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62948:25"/>impoſe, to us you juſtifie their Pleas againſt you, to be ſhort, you muſt bring thoſe things in, about which the difference is, either as Terms of Communion, or not; if you did not bring them in as Terms of Communion, then why do you criminate your Brethren as evil doers, whilſt you have nothing againſt them, but refuſing compliance with your Opinions? As this ſhews the want of Charity, ſo 'tis no proof that your cauſe is good; but as you bring them in as Terms of Communion, whilſt they are no eſſential things, you muſt be wrong, whether the things be wrong or nay; for if brought in as Terms of Communion, whether right or wrong, they muſt be received.</p>
            <p>Therefore, as the liberty of choice is taken away, our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is ſuperfluous; ſuch ſervice indeed may be blind or worſe, but can never be reaſonable: This appears as an exceſs in you, and as every exceſs is a wrong, for which you muſt plead the light within, or ſome other thing; if ſome other thing, pray let us know what it is in the mean time, as this is a wrong, muſt it not be oppoſed by ſuch as ſee it a wrong, by ſetting the meaſure of Underſtanding God has given, againſt this wrong, how elſe ſhall wrong now, or any for the future be redreſſed?</p>
            <p>If this be what our Author terms Confuſion, and ſetting mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure againſt meaſure, are not you firſt in the matter, by admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the occaſion, ſetting your meaſure not only againſt, but over your Brethren? For in the Truth, to us it doth not appear, but your Brethren have as much power to refuſe things, as you can have to impoſe; and where the power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> equal, the difference about Opinions in circumſtantials ought to be diſcontinued by thoſe that gave the occaſion; for we are ſure it is more according to Truth, for you, to omit the doing of what you may believe is good in this ſenſe, than for others to receive what they believe is wrong; it will not be your calling them requiſite things that can give you any Authority; for ceremonials or circumſtantials, will ſtill be ſuch, when you have ſaid and done what you can.</p>
            <p>But if this be <hi>Babel</hi> indeed, a Term of his own ſtarting, are not you the Maſter Work-men in this building, the cauſe for which the Language is divided? And then, is not there a plain parallel betwixt your work, and that in the Land of <hi>Shiner?</hi> They were there of one Language while they journyed, and till they began to build, their end was Preſervation as well as yours; but as they
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62948:25"/>took their own Counſel, and not the Lord's, he divided their Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, not for their hurt, but that they might be ſtopped (which otherwiſe they would not) in that fruitleſs labour, that as it could never be perfected, ſo it could not anſwer the end de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned.</p>
            <p>And like to this, was not we of one language whilſt we truly travelled for the true reſt of the Soul, to wit, Union and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, in that holy Spirit of his Son Chriſt Jeſus? But when we found <hi>Shinar</hi> a Plain, and took up our dwelling there in the likeneſs of Truth, then did not we, as others before us, begin to build, and bring in the Brick inſtead of the true Stone, and Slime inſtead of the true Mortar, proper Materials indeed for a great Building, and yet but the product of Man's reaſon? and though our end was Preſervation, yet foraſmuch as thoſe Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials that makes this our Building, cannot regenerate the Soul, nor make the Mind holy, and as over-valued, hath ſtopped our Travel and Journeying, the Lord has looked down to behold our work, and becauſe it cannot anſwer the end deſigned, and we would not be ſtopped otherwiſe has he not as of old, and often ſince, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided our language, not for our hurt, but for our good, if we could but make the true uſe of it, which is to ceaſe our Building, our Works, and ſo return to him that did begin to work in us by his holy Spirit; for he only can perfect it, and reſtore to us not only one language, but the pure language which can never be done any other way; for no hopes of doing it by our ſtrength and work; for that cauſed the diviſion, that way we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Sect, but can never be born of God's univerſal Spirit, where that one Original language is known, to which all that fear God muſt at laſt be gathered; till this is known, as there has been turnings and overturnings, on this account, ſo it muſt ſtill continue till he come to rule, whoſe right it is: We wiſh in the love of God it could be truly weighed and conſidered, before it be too late.</p>
            <p>And in the mean time, for you to call ſuch Pleas as thoſe, <hi>leave me to the Grace of God, and to the Spirit of Truth looſe Pleas together,</hi> with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſuch like mentioned in his Book; we muſt ſay, we look upon it as of dangerous conſequence; what though ſome may abuſe them, will you take them away, and with them freedom of Speech? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you demoliſh thoſe Fortifications that the Truth hath reared againſt Impoſition, Innovation, and in ſome ſort provided againſt an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62948:26"/>This appears to us the fore-runner of a Retreat, as others before us have done, who begun with the Spirit, but after ſought to be made perfect by ſome outward way or thing.</p>
            <p>For if ſuch Pleas and Teſtimonies of truth as theſe, <hi>that nothing is a Duty but what we are perſwaded on, and that we ought to be left to the Grace of God,</hi> becauſe the Spirit of Truth is the only guide into all Truth, be diſcouraged ſo early, and freedom of Speech taken away, what may we think the next Age may do, when we conſider, there was not yet any Chriſtian Society, but did at long run de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline its Integrity, in which danger we ſeem as well as any that did go before us? And his own words to us, ſeems to import as much, for he brings the young convinced to be in moſt danger, and for whom thoſe requiſite things ſeems moſtly alledged to be ſerviceable, is this, becauſe the Truth grows old, that outward things are joyned with it to aſſiſt it, nay, ſure then it muſt be becauſe there ſeems a decreaſe; and if the young convinced ſeems in this great danger, whilſt the old are living, what muſt they do when they are gone beſide, if not an increaſe, there will be a decreaſe?</p>
            <p>Well, ſince there is danger to go backward from the Truth, in the Mind and Love of God in the Heart, either into the World, or into Form without Power and Life, why ſhould not liberty of Speech be allowed to all, yea, to ſuch as think themſelves the Church? For if not ſuffered now, becauſe you think you are right, they will not be allowed when there is need, becauſe they are wrong, eſpecially having your early Example to plead; and thus may Truth's Teſtimony ſuffer in the future, by the cauſe which you now have given; wherefore we think, ſince you ſeem to make ſo much Poviſion for future time, you ought in this more eſpecially, to have ſet Poſterity a good Preſident by your Moderation and Forbearance, why may not you be cautioned to beware of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality? We would gladly have a ſatisfying reaſon for this, while we conſider all before us have failed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re, and what can you ſay more in our day, than others before us could in their time? Have you received more? then more is required. Have you any thing but what you have received? Muſt not the Roo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bear yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and not you the Root? Muſt particular Perſons by our own Rule be humble and low, and think others better than themſelves, and muſt not Churches as they relate to Aſſemb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>, read in the ſame book, for they are made of the ſame Men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:62948:26"/>
            <p>Are they holier for being aſſembled, or becauſe the greater number? then let them be more humble too. We believe it is as much the duty of Aſſemblies, as of Individuals; for at beſt you know but in part, and there is yet that to know, which you do not; and God is no more bound to many, than he is to one; as the Wind blows where it liſteth, ſo may God ſpeak or appear by whom he pleaſes: Pray let us know why Truth's Teſtimonies may not be allowed, and paſs currant, where the Life and Converſation is ſuitable; is it becauſe you are the greater number, or becauſe there is ſome among this greater number that is infallible, and then have received the whole Counſel of God, that nothing can be true but what ſuch allow of, and all muſt be ſo that they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove? Not the firſt ſurely, for Truth never proſpered in the World, while that was to be Truth, concluded by the greater number; beſides, 'tis from hence that the Whore takes her power and ſtrength, ſo that its not leſs than a ſcandal to ſpeak of it, in the caſe; but if the latter, we muſt confeſs 'tis rare if true, becauſe without Preſident or Example; but on the contrary, that many have pretended as high things, and yet have been wrong, is no news, why then ſhould not you fear, that while you think you ſtand, leaſt you fall? For we believe you cannot make it appear, that any pretended ſuch high things but they failed.</p>
            <p>So that by all we can find, you ſeem in more danger than ſafety, and conſequently more occaſion to bear, if not receive thoſe Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, than reject them, under the notion of looſe Pleas.</p>
            <p>Perhaps you will ſay, that thoſe that uſe thoſe Pleas are wrong, and therefore the Teſtimonies are falſe and wrong, as uſed againſt you; but thoſe that uſe them will tell you, that they really con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern you, and that they are for your good to regard them, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are ſo, for any thing that we can find that you have ſaid or done; but if ſome have been wrong, muſt all be condemned for that? Will that make you right? We doubt not, but you ſay, they are wrong, if ſo, it muſt be manifeſt in their Lives and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation or not. If manifeſt in their Lives and Converſations, place your Judgment upon what is evil, and ſpare not, for there it will ſtand; for we plead not for evil in any, but for what is good; but let that which is true, live; you know where the Heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth to Righteouſneſs, the Mouth muſt confeſs unto Salvation;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62948:27"/>ſo where the Spirit of Truth is owned, and known the guide into all Truth, ſuch may truly hold forth thoſe Teſtimonies which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto it, yea, for thoſe Teſtimonies of Truth ought to live, as outward Monuments of it through all Generations. But if no evil manifeſt in their Converſation, nay, perhaps inſtead of find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any evil there, their Lives and Converſations may be as good as yours, and ſuch as adorns the Goſpel, againſt which Scripture ſaith, <hi>there is no Law;</hi> will you then make Laws againſt ſuch as God has made none? What will you do now? Will you ſay they are ſtill wrong, though you have nothing againſt their Lives and Converſations, nor yet againſt any principle or eſſential thing they hold, and that becauſe of that wrong, thoſe Teſtimonies of Truth which they uſe, are wrong and falſe?</p>
            <p>For he ſaith Page 9. <hi>That a ſaying may be falſe or true, according to the ſubject or matter it is applied too;</hi> but that we believe is a miſtake; for we think Truth's Teſtimonies are not falſe, becauſe ſome may miſ-apply them. For inſtance, this Teſtimony that the Spirit of Truth is guide into all Truth, is always true, however miſ-applied, to illuſtrate it in lower things, as Meat, Drink and Cloathing, then what is more abuſed or miſ-applied; are they wrong or falſe, becauſe ſome abuſe them? No ſuch matter; no more do we think Truth's Teſtimonies falſe, becauſe ſome abuſe them.</p>
            <p>Will you then abuſe and diſcourage thoſe Teſtimonies, becauſe you think thoſe are wrong that uſe them, though nothing that is immoral, or evil in it ſelf, can be proved againſt them? We think you cannot do this in the beſt ſenſe, but do evil that good may come of it; and though that may be a Maxim in a falſe Church, we believe 'tis none in a true; are they wrong ſtill in your thought? then 'tis what you cannot right without doing wrong your ſelves. Now, if you cannot right a thing without doing wrong, is it not your place to ſuffer? Nay, is it not your Duty? And if the advice to the Church of <hi>Philadelphia</hi> was thought on in this caſe, it might help to ſupport: However, we know our Saviour overcame by ſuffering, and muſt not all that's born of his Spirit, overcome by the ſame way, when they cannot do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe but do wrong? Otherwiſe do not you put forth your ſtrength, inſtead of waiting for God's, and that we believe will ſpoyl the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62948:27"/>work? Doth. Truth's Government ſeem to totter? What then? Is not the Government of truth God's? Cannot he eſtabliſh it without your ſtrength? Remember <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zza</hi> put forth his hand to ſtay the Ark when it ſeem'd in danger, he could plead his end good as well as yours, and yet he ſuffered for it; there may be an over-carefulneſs, as well as too little.</p>
            <p>But might not a little Charity help all this, could you look upon ſuch as trouble you to be conſcientious, which we think you might ſafelier do, than make ſuch Tranſgreſſors and evil-doers, for refuſing circumſtantial or ſhadowy things, while they own with you, that without Holineſs no Man can ſerve the Lord; for how can this preach to them that are not of our Communion, while you give not unto your Brethren, what you deſired to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from others? This we think you might eaſily do, while you differ not in eſſentials; for as you differ not in eſſentials, there ſeems nothing but what might be diſpenſed with. Remember they obtrude nothing upon you, nor ſeems to ſtand for any other free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom but that wherein Chriſt has made them free; therefore, if you could eſteem them, or any of them conſcientious, the work would be eaſie. You know the Lord often ſpared thoſe that are wrong, for the ſakes of thoſe that are right, and 'tis our Doctrin, Tares ſhould be ſuffered to grow, rather than deſtroy Wheat; then how can your Government be like his, whilſt that is wanting? Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you cannot think that all is wrong that are diſſatisfied with thoſe new things brought in, at leaſt, as made Terms of Communion. We would perſwade you better if we could, by aſſuring that ſome are right by being ſincere; could you but believe this, you would quickly find all that is lawful is not expedient. Here the work would be eaſie, nay, your duty too, to omit the preſſing to diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, ſome things that you might think good, whilſt in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves no eſſential things, rather than put your Brethren upon the receiving things that are not good, which all ſuch things are that are not of Faith; you know who hath ſaid it.</p>
            <p>But if this difference cannot be ended, but that it muſt be like that of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> manage it with more Moderation, and in that love of God, that it may be ſhewed the Lord is at hand, to gather different apprehenſions into a better tempe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; and thus in your difference, there might be true ſervice by ſhewing the World
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62948:28"/>that Chriſtian Example, which as yet they never had, and do as much want, otherwiſe you will diſhonour the God of Truth and Peace, before the People: It will not be the laying the blame one of another, that will do the buſineſs, you muſt agree together quietly, or part friendly, or you are no preachers of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, whatever your Principles of Truth may be: <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and <hi>Lot</hi>'s, could not agree together, but they agreed in their parting, nor did their ſeparation loſe their Friendſhip, as the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of love performed after, do manifeſt, at leaſt, on <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s part, who was the greater, more by his Self-denial and Meekneſs, than his Elderſhip; for he was content for quietn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs, with what the other left or refuſed.</p>
            <p>But why cannot you agree together, whilſt you own one and the ſame righteous Principle? You came out together, have you not done the greater, and cannot you do the leſs? That's ſtrange; were it not worth your while ſeriouſly to conſider, that the Lord may have a hand in the matter, than ſtill either think of differing or dividing? Had not you need conſider, that all before us that have come out through the ſtiring of God in their Mind to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, was not only tryed by ſuch as was wrong, but alſo by ſuch as was right? In the firſt, they ſtood, but in the latter have failed, and can we think to be made perfect without the full Trial, if you think that therein is your danger? O that this could be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in that coolneſs, love and good will, that 'tis written in! For certainly this is our Trial.</p>
            <p>But that we may come to an end, ſeeing there has been ſo much ſaid by him of the Church, and power of the Church, we deſire to know what is meant and intended by this word Church, for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the whole Communion is taken for the Church, and ſometimes every particular Society have the name of the Church; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, becauſe of thoſe divers acceptations of the word Church, we deſire to have it ſet forth fairly, what is intended by the word Church, with reſpect to the Controverſie: In the mean time, we grant, that any may reprove evil, and what is immoral, in any of the ſame Society, we grant, that any Aſſembly that meets about the outward Affairs of the Community, may deal with ſuch as go from Truth's Principles, or goeth into any thing that is immoral, or
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62948:28"/>that layeth any other Foundation than Jeſus Chriſt, and his holy Spirit, to be guide into all Truth. But foraſmuch as the difference is not about any of thoſe things, but about certain new things that have been brought in ſince our beginning; on this account we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be ſatisfied, where that power remains to bring new things in, and to make ſuch things Terms of Communion; and to this end, we offer, either ſuch things muſt have a value in themſelves, or they muſt have a value ſet upon them by others.</p>
            <p>If the firſt, they will ſpeak for themſelves without any unſound or untrue Argument to defend them, or force them forward; for thoſe are ſo far from helping any good cauſe, as they really hurt it; for how ſhould we believe that cauſe good, which we know not, but by thoſe Arguments which we are ſure is falſe, or at leaſt not true?</p>
            <p>But if the latter, then others muſt ſpeak for them, and we muſt receive them, not becauſe we know they are true and good by their own worth, but for the value of thoſe that bring them in, which we think muſt be either ſome particular Perſons, or elſe ſome Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: If the firſt, who, and where are they, and from whence does their Power and Authority grow? This can neither be peremptory nor impertinent; for if any ſuch thing, we ſhould know it; and every one that doth well, is willing to bring his deeds unto the Light; nor doth God lay an Office upon any, but he will ſupport them in it. But if the latter, then it muſt be an Aſſembly of the whole Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, or ſome particular Aſſembly; not the firſt, becauſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not meet to conſult, not the particular meeting that our Author belongs too, nor that which we belong too, nor any of that Order; for then, as there is as many Churches as diſtinct Aſſemblies, there might be as many Opinions as Churches, their Power being all alike.</p>
            <p>If then ſome diſtinct Aſſembly, it muſt be ſuch an one, to ſpeak modeſtly, as is ſuperiour to all the reſt, according to Conſtitution, and then what comes not in this way, can have no ſhadow of any Authority, for force or preſſure of new things, beyond ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and freedom; but ſuch a Church cannot be, but either by a civil Compact, or by a divine Inſtitution: The firſt is not agreeable with the Truth, for we cannot delegate, or give power to any to make Rules or Laws, to guide us, or oblige us in ſpiritual Matters, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62948:29"/>we cannot be bound by any thing but the Truth, and we muſt know it ſuch, before we can be bound by it; therefore no ſuch Compact or Agreement can be, becauſe liberty reſerved, and our power given away, are inconſiſtent. But if the latter, that ſome one Aſſembly, according to divine Inſtitution, is ſuperiour to all the reſt, who can make circumſtantial or ſhadowy things Terms of Communion? 'Tis neceſſary we ſhould know that Aſſembly as well alſo, that their Authority is divine, if we muſt reſt upon their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations without Trial in theſe matters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this we think we cannot know but by a divine way, and that then muſt be either by a divine ſenſe in our own minds, or by the Authority of Truth which ſuch bring to convince in both caſes; we conceive our Underſtanding is concerned in our Obedience and Duty, but neither of thoſe ways are known to us at preſent; therefore, till ſet forth to preſs Obedience under the notion of a divine Inſtitution, implies a kind of Contradiction, being in effect to ſay, we are to go out of the Truth to ſerve it; for to go into uncertainty, is not to ſerve the Truth, if it be not to go out of the Truth directly; thus by all our endeavour in ſearching into the matter, we cannot find according to the Principles of truth, that Conformity is to go before Conviction, however, not before Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion.</p>
            <p>And yet we ſay for Peace ſake, and that nothing might be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that is good, as alſo that true liberty may be preſerved, any Particular or any Aſſembly of the Community, may offer what is new, if they ſincerely believe it good and ſerviceable, without breach of Unity, or at leaſt of Communion; but we cannot find to the bringing of new things in, as matters of Faith, or Terms of Communion, that any Aſſembly have any more power than a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſon; and if miſtaken, we would very gladly be better informed; and therefore till that be done, we believe, to preſs new things, as matters of Faith, or Terms of Communion to diſſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and indeavouring to get ſuch things ſtrengthened, by get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the majority of Voices, either directly or indirectly, is a go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of Truth to make Parties. And this being done, how eaſie is it for Men to be hurried into that Uncharity, as not to diſpence with thoſe Diſſenters which themſelves have made, without Characters of Indignity, as publick marks of Diſ-favour, as
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62948:29"/>though the thing was out of doubt Truth, becauſe the moſt are for it?</p>
            <p>We ſhall endeavour to bring this long buſineſs to this ſhort iſſue, either ſuch as believe the Spirit of Truth is the only guide into all Truth, have liberty and freedom to judge of what they are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, or they have not; if they have not power and liberty to judge of what they are to receive and practice, as matters of Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then the power over them is uncountable, and ſuch muſt ſubmit to their Determinations, not becauſe they know, or are perſwaded they are true, but becauſe thoſe that have this power over them, ſay they are true; if this be not Uſurpation, exerciſing Lordſhip and Dominion, as well as the bringing in blind Obedience, and the begetting into an Implicite Faith, we deſire it may be fairly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated to be according to Truth; this cannot fairly be denied, becauſe we believe the Truth will ſtand the Teſt, and be willing to come to the Tryal; we know that which is falſe, will not indeed, becauſe it cannot; therefore we are fully perſwaded, where any is offended at this fair and free Inquiry, for ſatisfaction, 'tis a ſign, if not an infallible one, that ſuch are faulty.</p>
            <p>But on the other hand, if we have liberty and freedom to judge of what we are to receive and practice, as matter of Faith, on terms of Communion; that ſo our Religion and Duty, may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Underſtanding and Judgment, then we may diſſent, as well as aſſent to things propoſed or brought in, according as things or occaſion may fall out, and this, without fear or hazard of being proclaimed Delinquents; for Nonconformity, not only with reſpect to our private Sentiments or Opinions, for that we might do in <hi>Turky</hi> or at <hi>Rome,</hi> but with reſpect to thoſe of the ſame Communion, that would bring new things in to be obſerved, otherwiſe we have neither true liberty nor freedom.</p>
            <p>The Reſult is, if there be a power over us that can bring in new things, as matter of Faith and terms of Communion, let it be fairly ſet forth and proved, according to truth; but if we have power and liberty to judge of what we are to receive, then allow it freely that diſſatisfaction and difference may come to an end.</p>
            <p>To this we think can be but one Objection, and that is, that ſuch as are diſſatisfied, are not conſcientious, which we confeſs is an old Objection, but yet not more old than evil, and never was to ſeek
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62948:30"/>to abuſe others, by ſuch as over-valued themſelves; 'tis time there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were removed, being as well unchriſtian, uncharitable, as unrighteous, to criminate Perfons before any thing that's evil or immoral can be juſtly proved againſt them; and ſuch practices have always been ſo far from making difference leſs, as they made them greater; for inſtead of reſtoring the Path of Peace and Truth to dwell in, they always laid a ſure foundation, both for diſſatisfaction, and at laſt for diviſion, ſeeing every one that is truly conſcientious, have not far to go for an unerring Evidence, to reverſe ſo erronious a Judgment.</p>
            <p>Thoſe are ſome of thoſe many things that we are diſſatisfied with in his Book, and we can ſay on a conſcientious account, either then from a true Underſtanding, or from ſome miſapprehenſion of the matter; in both caſes, we conceive, we ſhould be relieved ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Truth. And as our Author is great in the Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Men, we expect, and alſo hope, he will be great as a Chriſtian too, which is to ſubmit unto the Truth where-ever it appears concerned, by amending what is amiſs, whether it be with reſpect to himſelf, or it be in our miſ-underſtanding, ſo far as lieth in his power; and that he may proceed chearfully in this undertaking, we are content to ſay, we know but in part, and indeed, we think but in a little part too, nor dare we think our ſelves ſo perfect, but what we have writ, may be objected againſt, by ſuch as will cavil on divers accounts. Perhaps ſome may ſay, it wants Method; may be ſome may ſay, there's ſeeming Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, or 'tis full of Tautologies; nay, perhaps ſome fault may be found as to the matter; for we confeſs and think, that the day will ſtill grow more clear, and then ſhadows will ſtill be leſs: However, as we are ſure our end is good, there can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing done againſt us in the ſame mind, that can hurt, or be of evil Conſequence; for varieties of Underſtanding, that ſtands in the fear of God, and are managed in his love, may be ſome cauſe that more light is afforded; but however, we make our advice to others, in the firſt place, a caution to our ſelves, to be always ready to hear and mind, what, when, and how the Lord is pleaſed to ſpeak or appear; for we do not already count our ſelves perfect; yet one thing we do, forget what is behind, and preſſes hard after the Mark that ſtands before,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62948:30"/>and think thoſe that do not ſo, ſeems not apt for the Kingdom of God; for the mind of Chriſt muſt be ſought for forward, and not back to his former appearances; and thus in part we know what we are, but what we ſhall be, we do not fully know; but as the living hopes remain in the mind, ſuch truly wait for his appearing, which as they cannot miſs of his coming, ſo ſhall they ſee him, as he is, and be purified by him that is pure, for he was, is, and is to come.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, we muſt confeſs, we do believe our Author might be really troubled touching our Differences, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> was about <hi>Ruben,</hi> when he built his Altar; but we believe alſo, he did not inquire the matter out fully as they did, which if he had, we are fit to think, we ſhould have found as few Objections in this Book, as in his other Writings; or had he conſidered of what, of this nature was, (as we were informed) communicated to him ſome time ſince, then perhaps had been no occaſion for this; however, we hope, ſhall be always as ready to confeſs unto a Truth, as to oppoſe an Error.</p>
            <p>In the mean time we conclude, truly deſiring the good of Mankind in general, but eſpecially of them that have in any meaſure believed, or confeſſed that the Spirit of Truth, or Light within, that comes from God, is the only guide into all Truth; for thoſe we are the more concerned, not only becauſe they are nearer to us by Profeſſion, but alſo, becauſe they have received more, and ſo have more to give an account of, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we do earneſtly deſire, ſuch may not ſit down in a Notion, or Profeſſion of ſo holy a Principle, and thereby take the name of the Lord in vain, but by a true Travel in their own Hearts and Minds, with God's holy Spirit, may come to prove the Truth of what is profeſſed, then will they be eſtabliſhed as Mount <hi>Sion</hi> indeed, that never can be removed.</p>
            <trailer>The END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
